<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The godly mans inquisition lately deliuered in two sermons before the right honourable Henry, Lord Montague, late lord high treasurer, priuie counsellor, &amp;c. other gentlemen of worship, at Kimolton on their annuall feast day. By R. Preston, Preacher of Gods word.</title>
            <author>Preston, Richard, d. ca. 1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20285</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111971</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847230</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847230</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12256</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10038)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12256)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1580:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The godly mans inquisition lately deliuered in two sermons before the right honourable Henry, Lord Montague, late lord high treasurer, priuie counsellor, &amp;c. other gentlemen of worship, at Kimolton on their annuall feast day. By R. Preston, Preacher of Gods word.</title>
                  <author>Preston, Richard, d. ca. 1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 65, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Dawson for Iohn Bellamie, and are to be sold at his shop at the two Grey-hounds in Corne-hill neere the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12256:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12256:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GODLY MANS INQVISITION, <hi>LATELY</hi> DELIVERED IN TVVO Sermons before the Right honourable HENRY, Lord MONTAGVE, late Lord High Treaſurer, priuie Counſellor, &amp;c. <hi>and other Gentlemen of Worſhip, at</hi> KIMOLTON on their <hi>Annuall feaſt day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> R. PRESTON, Preacher of Gods Word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Dawſon</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bellamie,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the two Grey-hounds in Corne-hill neere the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12256:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12256:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sr FRANCIS STANTON Knight, <hi>R. P.</hi> wiſheth to his preſent proſperitie the addition of <hi>many dayes in the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> feare of the <hi>Lord Ieſus,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Theſe two follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sermons, being preached before an honored aſſemblie whereto I was a ſtranger, I could not conueniently dedicate them to any perſon, or particular partie thereof, leaſt
<pb facs="tcp:12256:3"/>ignorance of their conditions, and want of knowledge and acquaintance ſhould accuſe me of preſumption, and too much boldneſſe: The remembrance therefore of your ſelfe, of your countenance, and fauour towards me became a ſudden ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, emboldening me to ſend them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad vnder your name: becauſe (as I am conſcious of your pious practiſes, ſo) I haue and doe know you a Patrone of Religion, and godlineſſe, eſteeming it your greateſt gaine to know Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and to be found in him.</p>
            <p>In theſe Sermons you ſhall find nothing ſauouring of Affectation, or inclining vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to oſtentation, but rather affection to the ſoules of the Flocke, for from the heart-roote in Ieſus Chriſt doe I deſire their ſaluation. The ſubiect of them is, <hi>The godly Mans Inquiſition,</hi> wherein you ſhall ſee the eſtate of man by reaſon of ſin and corruption layd open, <hi>viz.</hi> that he is a ſtranger to the Lord, a vagrant from the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> a loſt ſheepe, in bondage vnto ſinne and Sathan, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt, a child of wrath, a prodigall,
<pb facs="tcp:12256:3"/>&amp;c. And becauſe to looſe the fauour and countenance of God, is of all conditions the moſt miſerable, a vaſſallage without exception, I haue in the ſecond place ſet downe the meanes how to get out, which is diligent ſeeking of the Lord in prayer, faith, feare, repentance, holineſſe of life. Wherein alſo, that the dutie may be the more ſet forward, the place, the matter, the way, the manner, the meaſure, the end and time of ſeeking are in their due places propounded. And whereas there be certaine times when the Lord will ſpecially be found, and certaine times when he will not be found, I haue in the laſt place laid downe both, exhorting all men in the concluſion, to take the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent day, leaſt the ouer-paſſing of it through negligence, keepe them eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from it, and ſo bring them into euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſeparation from the preſence of God. This is an Abbreuiation of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, which I haue preſumed as ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with your allowance to publiſh. Be you pleaſed to accept it, be no ſeuere examiner, but a mild pervſer, and alſo a
<pb facs="tcp:12256:4"/>practiſer of the continents, and let affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the matter, ſomewhat mediate with your iudgement to cenſure not as you ſee, but as I meane. I confeſſe of my ſelfe, that I am vnable to carry the leaſt ſticke to the Altar, and vnworthie of all others to preſcribe either dyet or directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to any, that hath but touched the hem of Chriſts garment, yet am I not aſhamed to humble my ſelfe to others view, that by the mercie ſeene on me, who haue beene thus ſarre led into the ſecrets of God, they may be likewiſe encouraged to preſſe within the border of the Mount, when the horne of ſaluation ſhall be blowne. As I am I craue your pardon for my boldneſſe, and the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of your fauour, leauing theſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to your vſe and practiſe, and your ſelfe to the Lord, in whom I reſt euer</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>bound vnto you in all humble obſeruance,</hi> Ri: PRESTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12256:4"/>
            <head>THE GODLY MANS INQVISITION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ESAIAH 55.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Seeke the Lord while he may be found.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He foundation of my ſpeech for this time is grounded on this ſhort line, and few words of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah:</hi> and they well reſemble that excellent conſtructure of our SAVIOVR, laid downe in his Goſpell by <hi>Mathew: Seeke firſt the kingdome of God, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.33.</note> Where by <hi>firſt</hi> we vnderſtand, primarily, chiefly before all, and aboue all things: ſo that God, and his kingdome of grace muſt be ſought principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and require the firſt-lings of all our labours: For, as all Obligations which runne indefinitely without limitation of time (ſaith the Maxime in Law) are preſently due:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Simil:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſo we in the like kinde ſo we in the like kinde ſtand bound to God: And although in this Text
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12256:5"/>is prefixed no certaine day, yet it tells vs that wee are ingaged to euery day, and therefore all holy men vrge the preſent day.<note place="margin">Ier. 35.15. Gal. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>Turne euery man now from his euill way: Doe good while ye haue time. While it is called to day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 3.7.13.15 Ioh. 12.35.</note> 
               <hi>exhort one another. To day if you will, heare his voice: Walke in the light while you haue the light, &amp;c.</hi> The Mariner ſailes while the gale is fauourable. The Smith ſtrikes while the Iron is hote. The Traueller walkes while it is day; and the Lawyer takes his time: <hi>viz.</hi> euery tearme time: Now it is alwayes Tearme-time with Chriſtians: this preſent day is our Tearme, and ſo is euery day: If then we would haue our cauſe to be heard, Chriſt to be our Aduocate, and God to giue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence on our ſide, <hi>let vs ſeeke him</hi> diligently, and betimes;<note place="margin">Iſa. 8.13.</note> let vs earely in the morning ſanctifie the Lord in our hearts, and make him our dread.</p>
            <p>The Prophet hauing ſet downe in the former part of this Chapter,<note place="margin">Coherence.</note> the ſufficiencie and effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie of Chriſt, without whom nothing is auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſaluation (for in him is the fulneſſe of the God-head bodily) and likewiſe hauing deſcribed the calling of the Gentiles,<note place="margin">Col. 2.9.</note> and how they ſhould acknowledge Chriſt, and ſeeke the Lord; Here in this verſe from the occaſion taken from the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles he exhorts the Iewes to emulation: <hi>Seeke the Lord while he may be found;</hi> as if he had ſaid, ſeeing the Gentiles are ſo zealous, and ſo much enkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to ſearch the Lord, why ſhould you Iewes that are the Lords peculiar people be frozen,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.14.</note> and cold in this dutie? <hi>Seeke the Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words I will obſerue theſe three parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12256:5"/>firſt, <hi>Quid,</hi> ſecondly, <hi>quem,</hi> thirdly, <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> for the firſt, <hi>quid</hi> is the action, <hi>ſeeke.</hi> And this is taken from the courſe and practiſe of men, who hauing loſt any thing of moment and value, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelues to diligent enquirie, and ſeeking of the ſame, neuer deſiſting till they finde: So they that purpoſe to giue vp their names to Chriſt ſeeke God diligently, neuer giuing ouer their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions, til they be well aſſured of his preſence. To ſeeke God in this place, ſignifieth many things, as to labour to be reconciled to God in Chriſt, to turne to him by repentance, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation of ſoule, to worſhip and ſerue him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his word, to inuocate his holy name, to pray vnto him, to make profeſſion of his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to embrace him the true <hi>Iehovah,</hi> and as the onely God by a liuely faith, &amp;c. This large ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of ſeeking the Lord is not onely thus meant, and expounded here, but elſe-where in Scripture. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.6. and 27.8. <hi>While he may be found:</hi> Theſe words include the preſent occaſion, and time of ſeeking, for according to the time that God will be found, we are to ſeeke. Now if we ſeeke according to certaine rules after preſcribed, he will be found preſently, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are to ſeeke preſently.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>Now is the accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble time, now is the day of Grace.</hi> Otherwiſe there is a time when the Lord will withdraw himſelfe, and will not be found, though we ſeeke earneſtly, as the Prophet did for a <hi>Man to execute iudgement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>and performe righteouſneſſe in</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>and found him not.</hi> In few words, the meaning is this: O yee
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12256:6"/>Iewes by your diſobedience and daily tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, you haue loſt the Lords fauour and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, abuſed his gracious offers, delaying time, and procraſtinating Repentance, and you haue made vnto your ſelues Idolls that are no Gods: Now the Lord once againe offereth himſelfe in his mercies to your view, neglect not the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but ſerue, ſeeke, call vpon, and worſhip him: if it come to paſſe that meanes and time ſlip away through careleſneſſe, then all your hopes are in the winde, and you may ſeeke God, but he will neuer be found as a mercifull and tender Father, but rather as a terrible and a fearefull Iudge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seeke.]</hi> This word preſuppoſeth a former loſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 1.</note> we need not ſeeke God,<note place="margin">Sinne is the cauſe of the loſſe of Gods fauour.</note> vnleſſe formerly we had loſt God: Hence I gather this Theoreme, that by corrupt nature, and multitude of tranſgreſſions, we are looſers, not ſeekers of God, we are rather ſtrangers and wanderers from him, then Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of, and true conuerts vnto him. In the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of nature we loſt the comfortable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, which in our innocencie we enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: by looſing our ſelues we loſt him: and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the daily admitting, and committing of ſin after grace receiued, we looſe his ſight and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
            <p>Sinne is a make-bate,<note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> and a ſchiſmatique, that rendeth aſunder the ſacred bond of peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Creator, and his creature: it ſhorten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his arme, and withereth the freſh boughes of his loue: It maketh a ſeparation betweene him and vs, as the Cloud betweene the brightneſſe of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12256:6"/>the Sunne and vs: It caſteth vs into darkeneſſe, and thruſteth vs behinde the doore, as <hi>Iael</hi> did <hi>Siſera,</hi> that we might loath to ſee the face of God, as <hi>Siſera</hi> did the face of <hi>Barak</hi> and <hi>Deborah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 4.18.19</note> So long as the <hi>Epheſians</hi> continued in their ſinfull I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie, they loſt God, for it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.12.</note> that they <hi>were without Chriſt, being aliens from the Common-wealth of Iſrael, ſtrangers from the couenant of promiſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no hope, and without God.</hi> And ſo ſoone as our progenitour <hi>Adam</hi> had tranſgreſſed the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, in eating of <hi>the forbidden fruit,</hi> he went and hid himſelfe in a buſh, as if Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence had beene too hot for him:<note place="margin">Gen. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>Adam and his wife hid themſelues from the preſence of the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the trees of the Garden:</hi> fearefull they were to heare him ſpeake, and aſhamed to ſee his face, and therefore they ſeeke ſtarting-holes, to hide themſelues the further from him. In the ſame tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are all his of-ſpring to this day, if the old ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent get any of vs to plucke an apple from the prohibited tree, that is, if he winne our conſents to ſinne, he hath his deſire, and we become vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds on the earth, and fugitiues from the face of God: And euer the more we offend, the further we are from God, being either like Pilgrimes now wandering vp the ſteepe Mountaines of pride, now downe the low vallies of deſpaire, now through the ſhadie groues of wantonneſſe, now through the broad fields of licentiouſneſſe, now through the thornie thickets of worldly cares, now through the filthie channels of carnall luſts, roouing ſometimes here, ſometimes there, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12256:7"/>mate and guide, the Deuill leading vs whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he liſt, or like Marchant aduenturers, imbarkt in the ſhip of ſecuritie, ſometimes hoyſing vp the ſailes of noyſome deſires, ſometime filled with the merry gale of vaine and worldly pleaſures, ſomtimes delighted with a whiſtling aire of filthy lucre, euer and anon running vpon the Syrtes and quickſands of ſinne, to the great danger, not ſo much of the loſſe of life, and wracke of goods, as the wracke of Conſcience, which is the greateſt ſhipwracke, and the loſſe of Gods lone and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is the greateſt loſſe. Thus ſinfull men that we are, whileſt with the Prodigall we become trauellers, and Marchant aduenturers, to ſee the faſhions of the world abroad, we become like to <hi>Ionas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ion. 1.3.</note> who <hi>fled to Tarſhiſh from the prefence of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be three things that make men forſake one anothers ſocietie;<note place="margin">Philo. de pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugis.</note> Hatred, Feare, Shame: for hatred, the enuious man hates the companie of him that proſpereth, and ſo doth one enemy hate another: <hi>Iacob</hi> fled from <hi>Laban</hi> becauſe of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice and Idolatrie, he hated them: For feare Children will runne from their Parents, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants from their Maſters, for feare <hi>Iacob</hi> fled from <hi>Eſau,</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> from <hi>Saul.</hi> For ſhame the Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer keepes his Cabin, and is couched in a cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> and for ſhame <hi>Adam</hi> ſkulted in the groue of Paradiſe: Tell me, thou fugitiue ſinner, for which of theſe things doeſt thou ſeeke to eſtrange thy ſelfe from God? there is no cauſe of hatred in him, for he is wholly delectable,<note place="margin">Cant. 5.10.16</note> 
               <hi>the faireſt of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand:</hi> there is no cauſe of feare in him, for he is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12256:7"/>
               <hi>the Father of mercies, and the God of conſolation;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.4.</note> he is rich in mercy, eſpecially to them,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>who haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the ſpirit of adoption to cry Abba Father:</hi> there is no cauſe of ſhame in him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.8.9. &amp; 25.3.</note> for he is the Lord of <hi>Glorie.</hi> Nay, rather (vile ſinner) be aſhamed of thy ſinnes, and bluſh at thy tranſgreſſions, whereby thou haſt loſt thy ſelfe, and a mercifull God: thou by thy wicked life, haſt turned thy backe vpon thy Maſter, and ſet thy ſelfe ſo farre at oddes with him, that thou ſhalt draw downe no loue from him vnto thee, vnleſſe thy Repentance and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation for thy ſinne, be as the Loadſtone to pull him to, and winne him againe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect:</hi> But how can a man wander from God,<note place="margin">Ob:</note> or loſe him? Whereſoeuer I am, God is there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; he <hi>filleth both heauen and earth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 23.24. Pſal. 27. Pſal. 139.2.3.4</note> he is with me at my ſitting, riſing, lying downe, in the thoughts of my heart, words of my tongue, wayes of my feete, nay, in my reines, and bones. His preſence cannot be auoided, who ſitteth on the Circle of heauen,<note place="margin">1 Reg. 8.27. Iſa. 66.1.</note> 
               <hi>and beholdeth the inhabitants of the earth as Graſhoppers, whoſe throne is the heauen of heauens, and the earth is his footeſtoole, and his wayes are in the great deepe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw:</hi> It is true;<note place="margin">Sol:</note> There is neither heauen nor hell, nor the vttermoſt part of the Sea, neither day nor night, light, nor darkeneſſe, that can ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate vs from God; the preſence of his God head is no leſſe in one place then in another: <hi>He is well knowne in Iury, and his name is great in Iſrael.</hi> But yet touching the preſence of his mercie, and lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſſe, that is not vouchſafed to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12256:8"/>they ſhall not enioy one iot of it: In which reſpect they may be ſaid to be farre abſent from God. Secondly, God may be ſaid to be found, when the kingdome of Grace is much aduanced amongſt a people: but the vngodly they ſeeke to ſubdue it,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> and <hi>to trample the precious bloud of Chriſt vnder their feete,</hi> which makes them ſtrangers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> Is it ſo that a man by ſinne flies the face of God:<note place="margin">For informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> this may then let vs ſee the malice of ſinne againſt our ſoules: It will neuer ceaſe ſtretching forth an Iſhmaeliticall hand, til it haue quite par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted God and vs, yea, till it hath diuided vs from our ſelues, for while we are beguiled <hi>with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceilfulneſſe</hi> thereof, irrationall conditions, and beaſtly qualities oppreſſe vs, and with ding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifts, and Prodigalls, it will make vs forſake our Fathers houſe, and change his ſweet and fat land for a ſtrange Countrey, his daintie cates, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of ſweet meates, for refuſe huskes, his friends and acquaintance to become fellow-feaſters with ſwine. In a word, it will ſo mad vs, that we ſhould neuer thinke either of God, or the Deuill, of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, or eternall plagues, if the Lord had not left time and meanes, that we might returne to our ſelues, and ſo ſeeke the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. Secondly, this Doctrine may teach vs to beware,<note place="margin">For inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> and to take heed of ſinne, and as much as in vs lyeth, to binde it to good behauiour (we haue no greater enemy in the world) ſeeing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our circumſpection, it will goe about to ſet God and vs at eares Oh then take the peace of it,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12256:8"/>and ſeeke to ſhut it out of the doores of thy heart, that it may neuer ſhut thee out of Gods preſence. And as <hi>Samael</hi> dealt with the <hi>Amalekites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.</note> ſo deale thou with the members of ſinne, kill them, and then bury them with <hi>Iezabells</hi> bones in a deepe graue, that they may no more riſe vp to hang vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee: this is the next and readieſt way to get into Gods fauour, and the preſence of his grace.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> 3. Thirdly, we are here likewiſe taught to bewaile the great loſſe of our God,<note place="margin">To bewaile our loſſe of God by ſinne.</note> and to lament the want of his gracious preſence: this is the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of euery godly man, for if he thinke it the greateſt gaine to obtaine the fauour of God, then he muſt needes thinke it his greateſt loſſe to want it. If there be any ſprinkle of Regeneration vpon thee, or ſparke of grace within thee, it will moue thee to griefe and ſorrow in the abſence of God, and compell thee to ſeeke him as the Hart doth the waters, ſaying,<note place="margin">Pſal. 143.6.</note> 
               <hi>My ſonle deſireth after thee as the Hart after the water brookes, and as the thirſtie lands after raine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> The reaſons why godly men bewaile the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, are ſpecially theſe two: Firſt, they know what it is to want God, by ſetting a priſe and worth on him, while they haue him preſent in their hearts: they know that when by ſinne we looſe him, the ſoule is dead, grace is withered, the Conſcience tormented, and heauen turned into hell; they know that the world cannot be ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable without a Sunne, nor the bodie without breath, as the ſoule without God, the ſunne of his Church, and the ſoule of the ſoule of euery true beleeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:12256:9"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, if God depart from them for a time in diſpleaſure, through their fall into ſome ſinne, and then leaue a ſenſe of his diſpleaſure in their ſoules, then their ſoules find ſuch a want of him, that they are not able to ſuſtaine themſelues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a preſent poſſeſſion: In this caſe godleſſe men being ſore afflicted, will mourne for their wants: and therefore much more the godly: But alas, for all this, with the moſt of vs it is farre otherwiſe, we can eaſily bewaile the loſſe of a ſheep, or a cow or an hogge, &amp;c. We will take on as a Beare rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of her Whelpes, and tell our neighbours our griefe, and the great loſſe we haue ſuſtained: but we ſeldome or neuer make any moane, that we haue loſt Gods fauour, becauſe we want a ſenſe and feeling of his bleſſings in his mercies: We ſeldome cry out in his abſence,<note place="margin">Pſal. 67.1.</note> 
               <hi>Lord lift vp the light of thy countenance vpon vs;</hi> neither doe we complaine,<note place="margin">Iſa. 59.2.</note> that <hi>our iniquities haue reared vp a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition wall betweene God and vs, and ſo hid his face from vs that he will not heare:</hi> neither doe we accuſe our ſelues <hi>as loſt ſheepe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 119. laſt verſe.</note> 
               <hi>that haue long gone aſtray.</hi> Oh therefore let vs flatter our ſelues no more with thoſe that plucke out the eyes of knowledge it ſelfe;<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.4.11.</note> 
               <hi>Tuſh, God is gone, he hideth his face, and will neuer ſee;</hi> But rather let vs reſolue to ſeeke GOD when he is wanting, and to mourne for the want. Let vs not follow our ſenſualitie too farre, nor buy voluptuouſneſſe with a price, but ſay with the Athenian Oratour, when we heare how farre God is from vs by our pleaſure:<note place="margin">Non em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m tanti peanitere.</note> 
               <hi>I will not buy the ſeeking of God by Repentance at ſo high a rate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:12256:9"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 4. Laſtly, ſeeing by ſinne we looſe God, here againe wee are exhorted, when we poſſeſſe him, when we haue found him,<note place="margin">Let vs hold God faſt when we haue him.</note> when we poſſeſſe to keepe our ſelues there, and to hold him faſt. Let thine eye be continually vpon him, and neuer ſuffer him to be out of thy ſight.<note place="margin">Pſal. 123.2.</note> 
               <hi>Behold as the eyes of ſeruants looke vnto the hands of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and as the eyes of a maiden vnto the hands of her miſtreſſe; So let our eyes waite vpon the Lord our God.</hi> As the child dealeth with his Father, he followes him vp and downe, and dare not let him goe out of his ſight, but holds hard on his skirts, &amp; keepes him with him; So deale thou with the Lord: turne thy ſelfe in euery good action vnto him, and if thou haſt any feare of looſing, then ſit the cloſer and hold the faſter, euer remembring that the ſecond loſſe is the greater, and bringeth more danger to the looſer: <hi>Dauid</hi> ſet himſelfe euer in Gods preſence,<note place="margin">2 King. 5.16.</note> ſo doe thou <hi>ſtand before the Lord</hi> continually, for this is a ſigne of thy obedience to the Lord thy Maſter, to ſtand before his face, and not to ſhrinke from his preſence.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the Suppoſition; Now of the Poſition, <hi>Seeke the Lord:</hi> Hauing laid downe, how that by ſinne we are out of Gods fauour, and loſe his preſence of grace; it remaineth to ſpeake of the meanes to finde the Lord, and to get into his fauour, and that is here ſaid to be <hi>Seeking,</hi> whether it be by prayer, Repentance, obedience, or hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word daily and diligently, &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">God being loſt by ſin muſt be ſought by all holy meanes.</note>And the Point is this, that hauing loſt the Lord by iniquitie, we are to ſeeke him againe by all
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12256:10"/>godly helpes and meanes: we muſt not ſtand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on arguments, but reſolue preſent diligence to ſeeke when God ſeemes to leaue the Cabin of our hearts, and begins to <hi>write bitter things againſt vs.</hi> The ſeruant put out of his Maſters ſeruice, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the profit by it, will not ſtand vpon his termes; My maſter did me wrong, why did he thus? but he ſeekes all meanes to procure his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters wonted loue and affection; neither doth it become vs (Gods ſeruants) to argue vpon points without ground, but rather we ſhould ſeeke Gods face when he calleth vpon vs to that purpoſe, ſaying,<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.8. Hoſ. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>Seeke ye my face.</hi> Thus did the men of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, they <hi>ſought the Lord,</hi> and he was fauourable &amp; gracious vnto them, God ſends not his work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men away without wages, nor thoſe that ſeeke him by Repentance, in faith, &amp;c. without a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.4.</note> 
               <hi>I ſought the Lord, and he heard me.</hi> He did not ſo much vſe his bodily feete to runne after the Lord, as the good temper of his affections to take delight in the Lord. Neither did he ſay, I prayed and was heard, but I ſought and was heard:<note place="margin">2 Chron. 20.3</note> and thus <hi>Iehoſaphat fearing God, ſet himſelfe to ſeeke the Lord:</hi> And why are all the Elect of God, called a <hi>Generation of ſeekers,</hi> but in reſpect of their enquiries after Gods fauour,<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.6.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it is the brand of the vngodly, that they ſeeke not God?</p>
            <p>And ſurely,<note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> if either the comforts and ioy we may reape by Gods preſence, or the neceſſitie thereof may be of force to perſwade inquirie, and to ſtirre vp our care, neither of them is wanting in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12256:10"/>this ſo weightie a matter: for comforts and ioy, what thoughts are able to reach to the excellency of them? Eye hath not ſeene, nor eare heard,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9.</note> nor heart conceiued the multitude and worth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: the preſence of great men will aſtoniſh and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze their inferiours, it will make them fearefull to behold their faces:<note place="margin">Math. 5.8.</note> but ſuch is not Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, his face and countenance is delectable, and <hi>at his right hand is pleaſure for euermore:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> and the more we can behold it, the leſſe is our feare; and the greater our reioycing:<note place="margin">1 Sam. 6.13.</note> when the Arke was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, the men of <hi>Bethſhemeſh</hi> exceedingly reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: when the publicke teaching of the Law (which had a long time beene diſcontinued) was againe eſtabliſhed,<note place="margin">Nehem. 8.12.</note> the people of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> were much comforted. But how much more will the <hi>Children of the marriage Chamber</hi> reioyce,<note place="margin">Math. 9.15.</note> when <hi>the Bridegroome is among them?</hi> This ioy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing from Gods preſence, concerneth either the qualification of the Conſcience, or the fruition of Gods fauour in the eſtate of glory: for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, when after many skirmiſhes, and ſecret terrors, it begins to gather heart (as we ſay) and to feele euidences of grace, then there is much ioy, yea, ſuch ioy,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.8.</note> as <hi>Peter</hi> calls it <hi>glorious and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable:</hi> Touching this Ioy looke vpon <hi>Dauid,</hi> boaſting in the <hi>ioy of heart,</hi> which was giuen him by the Lords <hi>lifting vp of his countenance vpon him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.7.</note> Looke vpon the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> going on in his way <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8.39.</note> becauſe he felt how faith in Chriſt was wrought in his ſoule; and that was <hi>Maries</hi> Ioy, <hi>reioycing in ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1.46.</note> that ſhe knew God in Chriſt was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12256:11"/>
               <hi>become her Sauiour.</hi> For the fruition of the ſtate of glory hereafter, it may well lift vp the beleeuers heart with comfort,<note place="margin">Reu.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall ſtand before the lambe</hi> accompanied with 24. Elders, <hi>ſinging and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing:</hi> he ſhall be <hi>where God is for euer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.16.17. 1 Cor. 13.12.</note> and ſhall ſee him <hi>face to face.</hi> If this glimmering light of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly knowledge (when we ſee but as in a glaſſe darkely) be ſo delightfull: what ſhall it be to ſee and know the Lord as he is? If the communion we haue here with Chriſt in his word, and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be ſo ioyous, what ſhall it be to enioy the immediate preſence of God our Father, Chriſt our Redeemer, the holy Ghoſt our Comforter? Now ſhall not ſuch excellent comforts, ſpringing from the enioyment of Gods preſence be reputed worthie our inquiries? What doe many vulgar people oftentimes to ſee the Kings face, or at leaſt his perſon? Strange things are done out of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thereof: As earneſt ſhould we be to get a ſight of God. Thus I haue briefely pointed you to the ioy of the Saints in their apprehenſions of God, and the beholding of his bright countenance: Now let me ſhew you the neceſſitie too: the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie in a word is ſuch, that without God, and the preſence of his grace, there is no poſſibilitie of admittance into heauen: for vpon all thoſe that are without the pale of his fauour, ſhall be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that ſentence paſſed vpon the man without the wedding garment;<note place="margin">Mat. 22.13.</note> 
               <hi>Binde them hand and foote, and caſt them into vtter darkneſſe,</hi> where ſhal be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comfort, nor light, nor yet hope of either. To be in a darke Dungeon, where is no penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12256:11"/>of light, nor any conſolation, is great paine and miſery:<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.9.</note> but to be excluded <hi>from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glorie of his power, is euen to be puniſhed with euerlaſting deſtruction.</hi> As is the world without a Sunne, a pining child without a Mother, a diſtreſſed land without a gouernour; euen ſo is the ſoule and body without the bleſſed and glorious preſence of God, nay, they are in a thouſand times worſe taking: for their exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be perpetuall and eaſeleſſe, their eye-ſight ſhall onely be of Gods wrath; and his eternall fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. They ſhall feed his Iuſtice while they are burning in fire and brimſtone,<note place="margin">Reu. 21.8.</note> which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death. Looke then of what neceſſitie, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and happineſſe, and life eternall is, of the ſame is the fauour and louing countenance of the Lord. If it be neceſſary for a man to ſeeke to be ſaued, it is neceſſary to ſeeke the preſent, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture good of his ſoule, by ſeeking a conioyning to the Lord by meanes of his grace. What can deſerue the very beſt, and (as it were) the very quinteſſence of our care, if not this?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi> But it will be ſayd,<note place="margin">Ob:</note> Why neede we ſeeke God, He is euery where at one and the ſame time, he fills both heauen and earth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In God we muſt conſider two things;<note place="margin">Sol:</note> firſt, Deitie, ſecondly, Preſence of Grace: touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the former, God need not be ſought, ſo he is alwayes at hand, as it appeares <hi>Act.</hi> 17.27. <hi>Wee may feele after him, and finde him, becauſe he is not farre from euery one of vs.</hi> And thus ſeeing his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, we ſee him. Touching his preſence of grace
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12256:12"/>(which is often wanting to comfortleſſe Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences) we are to ſeeke God, and are commanded ſo to doe: for he abſents himſelfe many times from his deare children, touching his Grace, ſo much, that they deſire but the leaſt impreſſion, and token thereof, and cannot get it, whereupon they are much exerciſed in ſtirring the ſcinders to finde ſome liue-aſhes, and will not giue ouer ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, till <hi>they haue gotten ſome treaſure,</hi> ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialtie of Gods fauour. And this is called the <hi>ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods face.</hi> Pſal. 27.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But why ſhould we ſeeke Gods face?<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> Is it not ſaid: <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſee my face, for there ſhall no man ſee me and liue?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 33.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The face of God is either <hi>prima</hi> or <hi>ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol:</note> The firſt is the face of his ſpiritualtie, of his diuine Maieſtie, which cannot be ſeene with the darke eyes of mortalitie: Our weakneſſe is ſo great, and his Maieſtie on the otherſide is glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and tranſplendent, that we cannot behold it without the conſuming of our ſelues: no more then the eye can behold and looke vpon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding brightneſſe of the Sunne without the hurting and dazeling of it ſelfe. The ſecond is the face of his loue, and fauour; this with the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and <hi>the heart may be ſeene:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> ſaw this face of God, and reioyced.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. Is it ſo that euery one ſhould ſet himſelfe apart to ſeeke God by one godly helpe or other?<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> this then may ſerue to reproue the intollerable neglect of this dutie:<note place="margin">For reproofe.</note> Some ſay, oh, it is an eaſie matter to be acquainted with God, he may be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12256:12"/>ſoone found, a little ſeeking will ſerue the turne: but let the induſtrious carefulneſſe, continuall ſupplications, and the daily complainings of Gods ſeruants in the want of God, (yea, then when he is preſent in their hearts) teſtifie the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitie, and eaſineſſe of this buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi> I but Sir tell me, did not Chriſt ſay,<note place="margin">Ob:</note> 
               <hi>Seeke and finde?</hi> Therefore when, or where,<note place="margin">Math. 7.7.</note> or howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſeeking I ſhall finde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I grant it to be true,<note place="margin">Sol:</note> that Chriſt did ſay ſo to his Diſciples: and made this promiſe to them (in them to vs) that euery beleeuer, being in Chriſt, might ſeeke, and finde: but not that euery kinde of ſeeking ſhould obtaine. The meaning of the words is this, That whoſoeuer haue beene firſt ſought, and found of God, ſhall ſeeke and finde God: but they who haue not firſt drawne neare to him, ſhall neuer find God drawing neare to them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, another ſort of people there is,<note place="margin">2.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing much blame; namely, all ſuch as plead a perpetuitie of Gods preſence with them in the midſt of their wants of him: Oh, I neuer wanted the Lord, and why ſhould I goe troubling my ſelfe to ſeeke him? Alas, for the blindneſſe and folly of ſuch men: they ſpeake without ſence, to ſay they haue that which they neuer ſo much as once enioyed. Where God affordeth his preſence of grace, there alwayes are other companions of it, and ſuch as attend the Spirit: As we vſe to ſay, Where the King is, there is his Court, his waiters, his attendants; So, euen ſo where God is with his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12256:13"/>Spirit, there is his Court, and attendants, as ſaith, loue, obedience, feare, peace, ioy in the holy Ghoſt, worſhip, reuerence, prayer, Repentance, humilitie, &amp;c His Angels will be about thee, his Spirit within thee to helpe thee, his Grace to vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thee, his mercy to embrace thee: Looke then, are theſe preſent, then their Maſter cannot be farre off? But ſurely, Grace would tell thee (if thou hadſt any) that there is a great want of God, that thou maiſt ſeeke daily for a ſupply: and that he is the fartheſt off from ſuch as feele the leaſt want.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi> The Lord hath bleſſed me with his good Creatures,<note place="margin">Ob:</note> he hath giuen me proſperitie, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, I finde no want of them, and therefore if the, Lord were abſent from me, thoſe things ſhould be taken away, and I ſhould be depriued of their vſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> A man may enioy many outward bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,<note place="margin">Sol:</note> and in the poſseſſion, neither know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God loues, or hates him. He may haue his <hi>portion in this life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 17.14.</note> 
               <hi>and his belly filled with hid trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, he may be full of children, and leaue his ſubſtance to his babes;</hi> and yet he may be out of Gods fauour, and called,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.13.</note> 
               <hi>a man of the world. Eſau</hi> was fatted with the bleſſings of the earth, and yet he was ſo farre of from the Lords loue towards him, that <hi>the Lord hated him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the more couetous a miſer is, the leſſe acquaintance he hath with God, becauſe <hi>he is fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with noyſome luſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.9.</note> 
               <hi>and enters into many temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> which driues him from God: and therefore it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12256:13"/>was rightly ſpoken, that a Cable might as ſoone goe through a needles eye, as a rich Miſer enter into the kingdome of heauen, conſequently into Gods fauour.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">3.</note> another kinde of people deſerue equall reproofe with the former, namely, ſuch as leaue the pure Well and digge Ciſternes that will hold no water: ſuch as forſake God, and employ all their cares in and about the world. That ſeeke worldly pelfe, and externall goods, and in the meane time haue no regard at all to ſeeke the Lords good will loſt by their tranſgreſſions. It is now adayes an ordinary matter to ſee ſpirituall affaires iuſtled aſide, or rather thruſt out by the ſhoulders, that the outward man may receiue ſome contentment; and golden opportunity neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, that the occaſion of improuement of worldly commodities, of tickling carnal delights, and of maintaining outward reputation among men may be embraced. In a word, Matters tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching God are ſo ſleightly, ſo ſeldome, ſo remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſought after, as if they were not worthy talking of: And matters touching the world are ſo eagar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo induſtriouſly, and with that intention of minde and body followed after, as if God had made man for nothing els but to ſwallow downe goods and greatneſſe, as faſt as poſſibly he can. Oh, my Brethren, be ye in time recalled from this miſerable ſtate of miſery, and remember how faultie you are in ſeeking the things of God: your care for the earth hath ſo deuoured the care of heauenly things,<note place="margin">Gen. 41.20.</note> as if the <hi>leane Kine</hi> in <hi>Pharaohs</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:12256:14"/>dreame had eaten vp the fat. Conſider theſe things, and ſeeke the Lord in a good time, while the way is faire, the paſſage ſpeedie, the doore o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, the day laſts, and while he calls.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. As this Doctrine may reprooue the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender: ſo it may ſerue to inſtruct vs to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the point in hand,<note place="margin">For inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> to ſeeke the Lord: If a child in a crowd hath loſt the ſight of his tender hearted Father, or a waiting man the ſight of his kinde Maſter, or if any man hath loſt any matter of valuation, how diligently will they ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to Inquiſitions, they will goe euery way to the wood (as the Prouerbe is) they will not cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber themſelues with other triuiall matters found in their way, but paſſe ouer them as if they tooke no notice of them; So it ſhould be with vs, tho many good commodities may lie in our way, yet let vs neuer trouble our ſelues to take them vp, for it is a more valuable commoditie then they are, that we ſeeke after. Oh, let vs be ſtirred vp on all hands concerning this dutie, whet on one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other to the performance of it: And you that haue beene careleſſe herein, begin now at laſt to be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aduiſed, and thinke it not an eaſie thing to ſeeke God: Seeking requires a care, and an ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour more then ordinary. And you that haue beſtowed ſome care this way, be perſwaded that it hath not beene ſo earneſt, ſo conſtant, ſo intentiue as it ought to be, reamend and double the ſame. Yea, let vs all redeeme as much time as poſſiblie we may for this one thing, let vs abridge our ſelues rather in our outward profits, and purſuites
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12256:14"/>of them, let vs rather want opportunitie in our ſports, let all other things goe to wracke, rather then this one buſineſſe ſhould not be forwarded.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label>
               <note place="margin">For direction.</note> 
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. This point will teach vs in the third place a leſſon of direction, where, and how to ſeeke Gods louing face and fauour: And therefore if you be affected with the commoditie here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, you will be glad to take the time, meanes, and helpes offered.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">God hath three houſes.</note>Firſt, we will begin with the place where God muſt be ſought, for when we are once fully aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of his habitation (as I may ſo ſpeake) and of the place where he dwels: then we may both bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and freely ſeeke him. The place we muſt goe vnto is his houſe, there we muſt ſeeke him; for, as one neighbour hauing ſome buſineſſe with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, goeth not to a ſtrangers houſe, but to his houſe to ſeeke him: and indeed where ſhould neighbours ſeeke one for another, but at their houſes? So if the Lord be wanting to any ſoule (in as much as it crieth out,<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>why Lord abſenteſt thou thy ſelfe ſo long?</hi>) then let that ſoule be proſtrate before the gates of the Lords houſe, that he may anſwere the complaints thereof. And that it may not long be farre from him: Conſider that God hath three houſes, if we miſſe in one, or other, yet we ſhall be ſure to find in the third.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Firſt, Church Aſſemblies.</note>The firſt houſe where we muſt ſeeke God is the Church; whereto the godly often are congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and where alſo God is preſent after a ſpeciall manner: <hi>He is in the midſt</hi> of ſuch aſſemblings:<note place="margin">Math. 18.23.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn found the Lord in the midſt of the ſeuen golden</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 18.1.</note>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:12256:15"/>
               <hi>Candleſtickes,</hi> that is, the true Church. The ſpouſe ſought and found her beſt beloued <hi>in the tents of the Shepheards,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 6.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>and in the garden among the beds of Spices:</hi> that is, in the Aſſembles of godly people, where graces grow as Spices vpon a bed in a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. And ſo if we will finde the Lord, our reſort muſt be to the Sanctuarie: from vnder the threſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of the doore thereof,<note place="margin">Pſal. 63.2. And 73.17.</note> 
               <hi>flow forth waters to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh our ſoules.</hi> Thither went the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> in the time of diſtreſſe, and was comforted; and thither went the people of <hi>Iſraell</hi> to ſee the Lords face: So that in the Congregation (where the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle flocke of Chriſt is folded) we may ſeeke and finde.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of it is,<note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> becauſe thoſe meanes which God hath ſanctified, and ſet apart for our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and for inquiſition, are there vſed: there is the word truely and ſoundly preached; there are the principles of religion for thoſe of a lower forme; there are deeper points for exerciſed wits;<note place="margin">Heb. 5.14.</note> there are helpes for Magiſtrates, for Miniſters, for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men, for yong and old; yea, whatſoeuer grace is lacking, there thou ſhalt be ſure to haue it ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied abundantly; there thou ſhalt ſee the great <hi>Myſtery of godlineſſe</hi> diſcouered which is,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in the fleſh, &amp;c.</hi> And as in the materiall Sanctuary, the Lord reuealed himſelfe to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; ſo here to thoſe that with Conſcience ſeeke him will he likewiſe diſcouer himſelfe in the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of their ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> If God be pleaſed graciouſly to afford vs his ſight,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note> and remembrance in exterior temples,<note place="margin">For reproofe.</note>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:12256:15"/>where godly men are often aſſembled, then this may ſhew vs plainely the graceleſſe courſes of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ſinners, that liue as men without houſe, harbourleſſe, the bluſtring world is their lodging roome, vncleane birds their fellowes; and the houſes of ſtrangers their dwellings. Not to ſpeake of Separatiſts, who (as if our Church had vtterly loft her face, becauſe perhaps ſhee wants ſome beautie) doe flie from our Congregations, as if they were cages of vncleanneſſe: Nor of Popiſh Recuſants, who (becauſe they ſee not their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, their breaden and woodden Gods in our Temples) refuſe to come neare the portalls of our Church,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.42. Act. 20.27.</note> when <hi>the Key of knowledge</hi> (by which might <hi>be opened vnto them the whole counſel of God</hi>) is offered.</p>
            <p>Firſt, many others there be, who, that they may not be thought plaine Atheiſts, doe after a ſort ioyne with the Aſſemblies, not for loue to Gods houſe, nor for duties therein exerciſed (for ſo they caſt themſelues from the preſence of God in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lazineſſe, and prophane contempts,) but to ſhew their ſeruice of the time, and the ſauing of their purſes. The Prouerbe is, <hi>As good neuer a whit as neuer the better:</hi> It is as good to be abſent as to be dull, heauie, lumpiſh, and without ſpirit in ſeeking for God, whom they care not whether they finde or no.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Others in ſtead of going vp to the houſe of the Lord, ſeeke the vtter deſolation of it, (ſo ill affected are they with Gods preſence) <hi>they raze the Sanctuarie to the ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 74.7.</note> 
               <hi>defile the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12256:16"/>dwelling places of Gods name, burne vp the Synagogues of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>that no man may come to the ſolemne feaſts of Sion, and all her gates they delight to ſee deſolate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Many delight to paſſe ouer Sabboths in the Ale-houſe and Tauernes, being gathered to heatheniſh conſorts: Their vſuall ſpeech is this; the Church hath enough in it that may goe to God, and pray for vs, we may ſtay here well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Theſe paſſe vpon themſelues ſentence of excommunication, and like out-lawed perſons, are depriued of the benefit that belongs to the ſubiects of heauen (namely, Gods protection, and enioyment of his Realme) and thus they are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vp to Sathan.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.5. 1 Tim. 1.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Others take their horſe, and trauell uell about worldly buſineſſe vpon the Lords day, pretending that they can pray and ſerue God on Horſe-backe in their iourney as well as the beſt: But all theſe are deluded by the Deuill, whom they ſerue; they are cut off from the priuiledges of Gods houſe,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.18. Epheſ. 4.12. Rom. 4.11. Act. 14.27.</note> 
               <hi>The miniſtery of reconciliation, the bodie of Chriſt edified, the ſeales of Righteouſneſſe, which are by faith:</hi> And the preaching of the word, which is called, <hi>The doore of faith,</hi> is ſhut againſt them.</p>
            <p>And is it not a ſtrange thing, that whileſt they runne from God, from his preſence, his protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his Church, and Congregations, they ſhould thinke to meete with God, and finde him where he is neuer had? I may ſay aſſuredly they ſhall find him in his iuſt Iudgement, and he will meet with them in their hypocriſie to giue them a full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12256:16"/>they may goe on a while, but in the meane time, God is fetching a ſtroke againſt them, which like a flaile, the higher it is lifted, when it fals will giue the greater blow, and make the deeper wound.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. The Aſſemblies of the Saints is Gods firſt houſe where he will be found,<note place="margin">For inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> then ſhould <hi>we with gladneſſe goe into Bethel,</hi> for Gods name is there heard,<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.1.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt is there preſent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.20.</note> 
               <hi>and the preſence chamber is filled with the glory of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Reg. 8.12.</note> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaw and conceiued ſuch ſpeciall and extraordinary benefits comming to his ſoule by ſeeking the face of the Lord in his houſe, that he alwayes wiſhed himſelfe there:<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.4.</note> 
               <hi>One thing I haue deſired of the Lord, that I will require, that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the dayes of my life, to behold the beautie of the Lord.</hi> This was a matter which he deſired aboue all things, and for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining whereof he was very importunate with God. <hi>My ſoule longeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.1.2.4.10.</note> 
               <hi>and fainteth for the Courts of the Lord, bleſſed are they which dwell in thine houſe, &amp;c.</hi> Oh that the ſame minde were in vs to come before the Lord in publique meetings, and in them to be partakers of the exerciſes of pietie, then we would ſay with <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſurely, this place is reuerent, whatſoeuer we haue thought of it,<note place="margin">Gen. 28.16.17. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>It is no other but the houſe of God, euen the gate of heauen.</hi> This is the firſt houſe where God muſt be ſought.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Secondly, A Chriſtian mans familie.</note>The ſecond houſe, where God muſt be ſought is the priuate familie of euery Chriſtian. It ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth not to be diligent in the Church, vnleſſe a man be the ſame at home: this was holy <hi>Iobs</hi> care,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12256:17"/>that his family might be Gods houſe,<note place="margin">Iob 1.5.</note> as appeares by his daily ſanctification of his children: And of <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 24.15.</note> the Scripture truely relateth, <hi>That he and his houſe feared God;</hi> Intimating that while their houſes were receptacles of Gods worſhip, they themſelues (as they were Gods dutifull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, ſo they) were ſerious ſeekers of the Lords eternall loue and mercie. Our Sauiour ſaith, that whereſoeuer two or three are gathered together, or conſent in any thing in his name, he will be there preſent, though it be in a mans ſecret fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Adams</hi> houſe where God was worſhipped, and ſacrifices offered,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> was Gods houſe, whence <hi>Cain</hi> complaines he was caſt out, for euery denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is from the worthier part: therefore make thy houſe Gods houſe, and ſo thou ſhalt haue God neare thee, with his ſweete fellowſhip, and fulneſſe of bleſſedneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But what might I doe that my houſe may be the Lords houſe,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> to the end I may ſeeke and finde him there?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this purpoſe are required of thee theſe things;<note place="margin">Anſ.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. If thou wilt make thy houſe Gods Church, and ſo finde the Lord at home; then ſee that all the members in thy familie be the true members of the Church: looke to this with a diligent and heedfull eye: if there be but two righteous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in thy houſe, God will there ſhew thee his face after a ſort, but when thy whole familie may be baptized with the name of a Church, becauſe there is not ſo much as a <hi>Canaanite,</hi> or an vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12256:17"/>perſon in it, then it ſhall be as a ſweete ſauour in his ſight, and his glorious countenance will there be moſt radiant and bright.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Entertaine none into thy familie but ſuch as the Lord hath firſt entertained into his: take none into thine houſe which are not of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of Faith. This is the ſweeping of the houſe, and making faire of the doores &amp; gates for Gods entrance.<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.</note> The Prophets <hi>eyes were to the faithfull of the Land,</hi> that he might picke out the choiceſt of them for the Lords ſeruice, and his prayer was for the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that they might be corner ſtones, poliſhed, and grauen to make a Princely Pallace.</p>
            <p n="3">3. After this ground-worke is laid, then the houſholder muſt build thereon, dealing in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie, as the Paſtor in the Church; either by way of teaching by words, and example, or by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or by correcting. Firſt, teaching, and inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the familie is required, and that partly in reading, partly in deliuering precepts out of the Word. It is Gods Commandement,<note place="margin">Deut. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>To whet the Law continually on our children,</hi> and to traine them vp, euen from their childhood in the Scriptures. Secondly, Calling them to account for things deliuered by Catechizing is needfull. This is the driuing of the nayle to the head: this hinders vaine thoughts, words, and exerciſes: this bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth much folly, and ignorance that is bound vp in the hearts of children and ſeruants. Thirdly, Application of Gods workes paſt or preſent, on our ſelues, or others, to moue vnto confidence in God, by the workes of his mercie, and to feare to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12256:18"/>offend by the workes of his iuſtice, is alſo requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite: this was holy <hi>Abrahams</hi> practiſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 18.19.</note> for which God would not hide his ſecret workes from him. Fourthly, Edification of the family with <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> and melodie to the Lord is fit and conuenient,<note place="margin">Col. 3.16.</note> as the Apoſtle teacheth vs. Againe, as the Maſter of the houſe muſt teach by words, ſo by example, like <hi>Dauid</hi> walking in the vprightnes of his heart in the midſt of his houſe: for the eye of the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie is vpon the gouernours thereof, as the eye of the Church vpon her Paſtor.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there muſt be daily praying in the familie, at leaſt euery morning and euening ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly on our knees, making confeſſions of ſins, and requeſts vnto God, together with thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: <hi>Euening and morning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 55.17.</note> 
               <hi>and at noone will I pray, and make a noyſe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid.</hi> And <hi>Daniel three times a day prayed and prayſed God in his houſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 6.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, there ought to be in the familie Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Diſcipline, that if any member thereof ſhould happen to be out of order, by correction, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, reprehenſion, or at worſt excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it may be brought to reformation. By theſe meanes, the priuate houſe ſhall be made Gods houſe, wherein he may be ſoone ſought, and our ſelues ſweetly ſolaced.</p>
            <p>But alas,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> how careleſſe are the moſt in this caſe? Mens Cottages are Sathans Courts, and great mens places his Pallaces: How is God ſought at home, when (almoſt) euery member in the houſe is a rough, and vnhewed ſtone, not grauen after the ſimilitude of a Princely building? Is not ſin
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12256:18"/>ſo rife, that it runnes through the ſilent, and ſecret Chambers, and like leproſie defiles the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yea, the whole building? How is thy houſe Gods temple, when the Idoll of prophaneneſſe, diſorder, vngodlineſſe, &amp;c. worſe then <hi>Aarons</hi> molten Calfe, is erected? How doeſt thou flatter thy ſelfe with a conceit of Gods preſence in thy whole familie, when thou mockeſt him? Thou ſeemeſt humble at the Church, but art diſdainful, ſcornefull, hatefull, arrogant, and proud at home: thou ſeemeſt to be louing, kind, and friendly at the Church, but art full of malice, bitter words, frowning lookes, and vnkind carriages at home. Thou ſeemeſt in the publique houſe of God to yeeld obedience to wholeſome Doctrine,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> but at home (as the Iewes did deale with the bloud of Chriſt) thou trampleſt it vnder thy feete. How doeſt thou enquire for God in thy familie, when thou giueſt a welcome entertainment to Atheiſt, Papiſt, Iew, Pagan, miſer, ſwearer, oppreſſor, and others of the ſame ranke and ſtation alike? How canſt thou expect Gods preſence on thy right hand any where, if thou ſuffereſt thy houſe to be as a cage of vncleane birds, and neither pulleſt their feathers, nor ſweepſt out their filth? Oh, I beſeech you marke my words: The outward mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence and ſumptuouſneſſe of building, the pleaſantneſſe of ſcituation, the coſtly hangings on the walls, the rich furniture of houſhold ſtuffe, the goodly ſhew of tall, and proper perſonable men are nothing nay, outward ciuill order is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, vnleſſe all godly means with a godly mind
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12256:19"/>be practiſed as well in the priuate familie, as in Gods publique houſe. Labour therefore to make your houſe (by the induſtrious and honeſt exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of reading, praying, catechizing, examining, ſinging of Pſalmes, of entertaining, maintaining, retaining godly ſeruants: of puniſhing, admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, reprouing, or excommunicating vngodly and ſinfull people) like Gods houſe, then ſhall you haue cauſe of ioy, and matter offered ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of Gods preſence.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Thirdly, A ſanctified ſoule.</note>The third houſe where God is to be ſought, is the ſoule of a man. That is the temple of the liu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.16.</note> and he hath ſaid, that <hi>he will dwell there, and walke there.</hi> And often haue his ſonnes and faithfull ſeruants reioyced, that they might be in the leaſt ſort found worthie, that God would come thither. They ſought him in their hearts, and found him no where elſe, or ſooner then there.</p>
            <p>But how ſhall I make my heart Gods Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple?<note place="margin">Queſt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> As in the Temple God was daily wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped; there were daily ſacrifices offered, the Scriptures read and expounded, and prayers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred vnto God from his people: So muſt thou get a proportion in all theſe, if thy heart be Gods temple. Firſt, thou muſt priuately, yea, ſecretly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part daily worſhip &amp; adore him in thy ſoule with perſonall worſhip, concerning ſuch thoughts and impreſſions of his vnutterable Deitie, as the tongue in no wiſe can expreſſe. Secondly, Thou muſt offer the ſacrifices of praiſe and thankes, for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12256:19"/>his perſonall bleſſings, and benefits, call to mind how rich in his bountie he hath beene to thy ſoule, and ſo expreſſe thy humble thankefulneſſe vnto him. Thirdly, daily ſupplicate vnto him, and powre out thy ſoule in prayer vnto his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, deſiring the remiſſion of ſinnes paſt, preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſinnes to come, ſorrow and humiliation for ſinnes preſent, begge graces fit for thy ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſuch ſtrength therein as may vphold thee &amp;c. Fourthly, Solely and apart euery day reade the Scriptures, and other godly Treatiſes, as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion may giue leaue from honeſt labours, and being read wiſely, diſcreetly, vnderſtandingly, apply to thy vſe and benefit.</p>
            <p>Secondly, thy Heart muſt be as the Arke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Sanctuary, wherein were kept the Tables of the Law, written with Gods owne finger: thou muſt endeuour in obedience to all Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: entreat God to write his law in thy heart, that <hi>thou maiſt neuer depart from it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 31.33.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, thy heart as the Arke muſt keepe the Pot of <hi>Manna,</hi> a type of Chriſt the foode of life: cloſe Chriſt within thy heart, and hold him as thy life, neuer to part with him; for that Pot figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Sacraments, in which Chriſt is propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the food of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, thy heart as the Arke muſt containe <hi>Aarons</hi> rod that had budded, ſignifying the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline &amp; gouernment of Chriſt, vnto which thou muſt ſubiect thy ſelfe: let this rod flouriſh in thee,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12256:20"/>and ſtoope with reuerence and feare to this ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. By this meanes thy ſoule is Gods Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, where he will be found as a man in his houſe.</p>
            <p>But alas,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> though this be ſo neceſſary a dutie to ſeeke the puritie of heart, wherein is Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, yet who is it that addreſſeth himſelfe to it? Euery one is deficient in this point, the cleanſing of the ſoule is leaſt thought of for Gods habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And yet who is it, that boaſtes not of ſuch a good and honeſt heart, that makes not his brags of ſuch inward goodneſſe, as if God had dwelt there long? Who is he that complaines of his want of ſpirituall furniture for his ſoule? But looke to thy ſelfe narrowly, peepe in through the windowes, and thou ſhalt eaſily finde ſuch inward crazineſſe, and lameneſſe by corruption: ſuch halting betweene God and man, ſuch deadneſſe in ſinne and wickedneſſe, ſuch rouing thoughts, fleſhly deſires, carnall and worldly purpoſes, naughtie intentions, and ſuch defects of graces, as if thy heart had ſworne againſt Gods preſence, and made an vtter deniall of his entrance. Let theſe things be well examined, and tell me if it be not more then needfull to call for helpe, the ſpirit of ſanctification, to cleanſe and waſh all white within, to purge the ſoule from dead workes, and to make it a cleane houſe for God to abide in. The way to finde the loſt groat is to ſweepe the houſe, and to ſift the duſt: and ſo labour for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward holineſſe and ſanctitie, get thy heart ridd of deceitfulneſſe and hypocriſie, of ſinne and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12256:20"/>ſift the corners, ſet vp a light in it, the Candle of Faith, and vſe a proſpectiue continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally into euery farre nooke of it, and then get a weeding hooke to pull out Darnell and Cockle, ſo ſhalt thou not be long abſent from the Lord, at length to thy conſolation thou ſhalt finde him. Thus we muſt ſeeke the Lord in his houſe, the publique aſſemblies, our owne Families, and Soules.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12256:21"/>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:12256:21"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The ſecond Sermon.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Secondly, ſeek with the eye of faith and obedience.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Econdly, as we muſt ſeeke GOD in his owne houſe, ſo with a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall eye, as he himſelfe is a ſpirituall ſubſtance; fleſh and bloud cannot ſee him, though they ſeeke him: we can neuer finde him by the eyes of naturall ſenſes, but of faith and obedience: Gods ſpiritualtie cannot be pierced with the eye of fleſh, which ſeeth nothing but that which is finite, materiall, viſible, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcriptible, as God is not; nay, if the ſoule of a man, a finite ſpirit, cannot be ſeene with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily eye, much leſſe the God of ſpirits, who is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and of ſuch puritie as the Angels are not able to behold. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>No man hath ſeene God at any time;</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>God dwelleth in light not to be attained to, whom no man hath ſeene, neither can ſee:</hi> and therefore concerning the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſight (whereby curious and ignorant men would be glad to ſee God, hardly thinking there is any God, when none in this ſort can be ſeene) the truth is, God cannot be ſeene. Neither are we able to ſee and finde God by the eye of our mind, (whileſt we are here) as it is corrupted; the reaſon is this, becauſe all our knowledge is by formes
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12256:22"/>and faſhions conceiued in our minde, and for the moſt part floweth from the outward ſenſes, but God (as hath beene ſaid) cannot be perceiued by our ſenſes. No man euer ſaw the glorie of the Lord, <hi>viz.</hi> his Eſſence and diuine Maieſtie, no, not <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelfe, neither could he ſee him expreſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the eye of his minde. But thus farre we ſee the Lord, after an obſcure faſhion we ſee his loue and mercy, and kindneſſe to vs in the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of his ſonne Chriſt, in his beneuolent gifts of grace, in the remiſſion of ſinnes, iuſtification, ſanctification, &amp;c. But at the laſt day we ſhall ſee him fully in his brightneſſe and beautie, euen as he is:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12.</note> 
               <hi>Now we know him in part,</hi> ſayth <hi>Paul, but then we ſhall know as we are knowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Groſſe are thoſe old Heretiques,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> the <hi>Anthrope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphites,</hi> that gaue to God an humane forme, &amp;c. The Scriptures (ſpeaking after our capacitie) giue vnto him the parts of man, as feete, hands, face, &amp;c. And whereas they alledge ſome appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and viſions which the Fathers had; as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> of three going to deſtroy <hi>Sodome,</hi> as <hi>Lot</hi> of two, &amp;c. I anſwere, that God appeared vnto them not in his nature, but in ſuch a forme as pleaſed him. Many ſaw, <hi>Sed quod voluntas elegit, non quod natura formauit,</hi> What his will choſe, not what his nature formed. Men ſaw him when he would, in ſuch formes as he would, not in his diuine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wherein he lay hid euen then when he was ſeene.</p>
            <p>Groſſe likewiſe and ridiculous are our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conceits of God; Ignorant people ſuppoſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12256:22"/>him to be a man in ſhape and paſſion like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: The Epicure, who thought there was no happineſſe vnder the Sunne, but in carnall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, imagined God to be of the ſame ſenſuall humour, and deemed that freedome from buſines was his chiefeſt felicitie. And <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth in the Pſalme, that the vngodly perſon, who runnes to all manner of exceſſe, ioyning with the theefe, and partaking with the adulterer,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.18.21</note> and opening his mouth with the ſlanderer, thinkes God like himſelfe: and generally, our priuate thoughts touching God are not ſo holy, ſo reuerent, ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, ſo full of reſpect as they ought to be.</p>
            <p>Therefore if we would ſee the backe parts of the Lord, then we muſt pray to him to open the eyes of our mides, to cleere them with the grace of vnderſtanding, that we may ſee him now, not as he is in his eternall being, for that cannot be, but as he hath reuealed himſelfe mercifully and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly vnto vs in all his ſpirituall endowments of grace. This is the ſecond thing required in our ſeeking the Lord, namely, to ſeeke him not with the eye of ſenſe or nature, but with the eye of grace, enlightened and cleered.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Thirdly, ſeeke God by his meanes.</note> Thirdly, we muſt ſeeke God by his owne light and meanes: firſt, by the word in Precepts and Promiſes. This is a Lanthorne to our feete, and a light to our pathes, by which God may be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whom the darkneſſe of the world cannot comprehend. We reade, that when God appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Eliah, before him went a mightie ſtrong winde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 19.11 &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>which rent the mountaines, but the Lord was not in the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12256:23"/>wind. After the wind came, came an earth-quake, and after it a fire, but the Lord was in neither: but then at laſt of all came a ſtill and ſoft voice, and in that the Lord was.</hi> And that was it which moſt affected <hi>Eliahs</hi> heart; for, as the Story ſayth, <hi>When Eliah heard it, he couered his face with a mantell, and went out.</hi> Whereby the Lord would teach vs, that as in the firſt deliuery of the Law, the inſtrument which God taught them by was a voice (he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely forbearing to preſent himſelfe to their eies in a viſible ſhape, leaſt they ſhould ſtick too much vpon outward ſhewes) ſo they likewiſe in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing times ſhould truſt eſpecially to the ſame meanes, which God (as it were) by his owne mouth hath ſanctified vnto them at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, namely, a voyce. The nature of man rather affects that which offereth it ſelfe to the eye, then the naked and bare inſtruction of the eare: and therefore all counterfeit Religions are full of beautie, Images, ſignes, and bodily repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wherewith the world is bewitched. But the inſtrument that brings vs to the Lord is his owne word: the Lord thought it fitter to informe <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> by the care, then to giue him his deſire in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting himſelfe to his eye: ſo he doth ſtill hold the ſame courſe, and hath ordained the ſenſe of hearing, to be (as it were) the pipe, by which the ſauing knowledge of his will may be conueyed downe into the heart.</p>
            <p>And as for thoſe who will not be inſtructed by hearing,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> they are ſonnes of wrath, paſt all hope of] Gods louing preſence; there is no courſe, though
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12256:23"/>in mans reaſon neuer ſo little; that is able to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them. Let it admoniſh vs, if we deſire to know God, to prepare our eares to the meanes of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Remember what <hi>Salomon</hi> hath ſaid, that <hi>it is but the ſacrifice of fooles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 4.17.</note> which all thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, who <hi>come into the houſe of God, and are not neare, and readie to heare.</hi> thus much of the word, teaching vs, that a man deſirous to know in ſome ſort; or to conceiue the maieſtie of God, is inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more largely by the eare, then by outward and viſible repreſentments.</p>
            <p>A ſecond meanes to ſeeke God are ſuch ſignes of his preſence as he hath made choice of to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale his grace in. In the old teſtament beleeuers muſt ſeeke him in ſacrifices and ceremonies, and therein he gaue them gracious anſweres. The Arke of the Couenant was called the face of God, and the ſeeking of ſpeciall teſtimony of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence there, is called the ſeeking of his face. And becauſe he was ſo ſpecially preſent there, the <hi>Iewes</hi> in their Prayers muſt turne their faces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Arke, and towards <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And that the <hi>Iewes</hi> might know where to finde God at all times,<note place="margin">Exod. 25.8.</note> he told them that he would dwell in the Sanctuary, and ſit betweene the Cherubins: So in the new Teſtament, God hath appointed cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſignes, as ſo many way-markes to finde him out; as the publique ſeruing of him in ſpirit and truth; reſorting of Gods Temple, and there ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in holy worſhip with the reſt of his people, is the way to ſeeke him. The offering vp of the ſacrifices of prayer and praiſe, <hi>Call vpon me in the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12256:24"/>day of trouble,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15.</note> 
               <hi>and I will heare thee, and thou ſhalt prayſe me.</hi> The frequenting of the Sacraments, which repreſent that to the eye, which the word doth to the eare: In all which he will be ſought, and out of theſe will not be found. God cannot be ſeene, or found, but by his owne light, and therefore he that muſt ſeeke him, muſt haue the light of vnderſtanding.<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.2.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord looked downe to ſee if any would vnderſtand, and ſeeke after God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fourthly, ſeeke God in the right way. Ier. 6.16.</note>Fourthly, as we muſt ſeeke God by his owne meanes; ſo, in the right way, which is called, <hi>the old way,</hi> and therefore the good way: We muſt not ſeeke God that way we loſt him, for ſo it is likely we ſhall neuer heare of him: but there is another way, though a ſtrait and backe way, which ſoone brings vs to him. The familie of <hi>Iacob</hi> (thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentie ſoules) came downe to Egypt through the land of the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> but after fortie yeares cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cled about to <hi>Canaan,</hi> through the Arabian De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert. The three Wiſemen that worſhipped Chriſt were warned by the Oracle, to goe into their Countrey another way. Imitate theſe Sages, thou loſt God by tranſgreſſion, ſeeke him not in that common beaten way, but by obedience, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation: thou loſt God by adultery, ſeeke him by chaſtitie: thou loſt him by the way of pride; hatred, wantonneſſe, wrath, ryot, ſeeke him by the way of humilitie, loue, temperance, patience, ſobrietie: thou loſt God by the way of couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, contention, ſwearing, prophaneneſſe, ſeeke him by the way of contentation, peace, honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his name, holineſſe of life: thou loſt him by
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12256:24"/>the way of vaine ſuperſtition, ſeeke him by the way of Chriſtian Religion: to conclude, as thou loſt him by the way of ſinne, ſo now ſet on to ſeek him by the way of repentance, and reformation: A reformed life is the new way, and beſt way; till thou ſet foote in it, thou art out of the right way, and ſoone ſhalt looſe thy way to God: enter into it, and bid farewell to thy ſinnes, that thou maiſt with a quicke diſpatch, wheele about into thy owne Countrey.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, as we muſt ſeeke God in the right way,<note place="margin">Fiftly, ſeeke God in his owne manner. 1. Early. Pſal. 63.2.</note> ſo in Gods manner, and that is diuerſe ſorts of wayes. Firſt, Earely: This was the Prophets practiſe; <hi>Early in the morning will I ſeeke thee.</hi> That is, euery morning, the beginning of my worke ſhall be to looke towards thee; I will beginne my duties in faithfull inuocating thy helpe, and aid: And as in the morning of the day, ſo alſo in the morning of thy life, forget not to ſeeke God by Repentance, faith, obedience, &amp;c. This is the chiefe ſeaſon:<note place="margin">Eccl. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>Remember thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth.</hi> A wound lookt to at firſt when its freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt is ſooneſt healed; A groat newly dropt downe through the fingers, if it be preſently ſought after will ſoone be found: So will God in youth, from whence (as a friend) he hath lately departed, by reaſon of ſinne. Behold then, as euery day of thy life, ſo principally thou oweſt the prime part of thy life to this dutie, when thou art ſtrongeſt and apteſt.</p>
            <p>But many deferre to ſeeke the Lord, vntill the <q>laſt weeke of their life, the laſt day of the weeke,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12256:25"/>the laſt houre of the day, the laſt minute of the houre. It is an exorbitant courſe, while the ſhip is ſound, the tackling ſure, the Pilot well, the ſailes ſtrong, the gale fauourable, the Sea calme, to lie idle at Rode, carding, dicing, drinking, burning the ſeaſonable weather, and when the ſhip leakes, the Pilot ſicke, the Mariners faint, the ſtormes boyſterous, and the Sea a turmoile of outragious ſurges, to launch forth, and hoyſe vp ſaile for a voyage into farre Countries: and yet ſuch is the skill of euening ſeekers, who in the morning of youth, and ſoundnes of health, and perfit vſe of reaſon, though they cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue to weigh the Auchor, and cut the Cable that with-holds them from ſeeking of Chriſt, neuertheles, they feed themſelues with a ſtrong perſwaſion, that when their wits are diſtracted, their ſenſes aſtonied, all the powers of the mind, and parts of the body diſtempered; then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, they thinke ſuddenly to become Saints at their death, howſoeuer they demeaned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues as Deuils all their life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs awake from ſinne with <hi>Dauid</hi> early,<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.9. 1 Sam. 15.12. Gen. 21.14. Ioh. 8.2. Ioh. 20.1.</note> riſe with <hi>Samuell</hi> early, with <hi>Abraham</hi> ſend away <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> early, with Chriſt and his Audience come to the Church early, ſeeking the Lord with <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> early: Of this point more largly touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the opportunity of ſeeking, hereafter follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Secondly,<note place="margin">2. Earneſtly.</note> Earneſtly; As the husbandman for gold, ſiluer, and his earthly Commodities, ſo we muſt ſeeke for this ſpirituall and eternall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: the former ſeekes eagarly, and inſtantly, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12256:25"/>ſo muſt we. Our deſire as it is to enioy, ſo it muſt be earneſt and feruent in the purſuit; we ought to neglect no time, nor pretermit any the leaſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of finding. A loitering man that cares not whether he worke or no,<note place="margin">Prou.</note> may get for his idleneſſe a ſuit of ragges: and he that thinkes to gaine Gods graces with nothing adoe, may well goe without them. There goes the ſtriuing for maſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries before the Crowne; a painfull ſweating race before the getting of the goale, and an induſtrious diligence (notwithſtanding all ſerious thoughts to this purpoſe) before the obtaining of the Lords grace and fauour.</p>
            <p>Seeke painefully, not careleſly, not ouerly,<note place="margin">Luke 15. Pro. 2.4.</note> as the woman for her groat; <hi>ſeek as for ſiluer, ſearch as forgold.</hi> The mint of gold lies not in the firſt ſpade it lies deeper: ſearch with a deſire of finding; for its well if after all paines, we finde at the laſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Sincerely,<note place="margin">Thirdly, Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely.</note> with a good and honeſt heart. <hi>Quod cor non facit, non ſit;</hi> What the heart doth not is not done at all. <hi>Adams</hi> body being newly framed of the ſlime of the earth, lay liueles and breathleſſe, vntill the breath of life was brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed into it; So the action of ſeeking God, with all the circumſtances and tearmes thereof, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth in the ſight of God, vntill from the Altar of the heart, the fire of zeale, ſinceritie, and integritie incenſe them.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.10. Rom. 6.17. Rom. 10. &amp;c. Deut. 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>S. Peters hidden man of the heart, S. Pauls obedience from the heart, Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of the heart, &amp;c.</hi> are acceptable to GOD. Therefore in our ſeeking the Lord, let our heart march along, that ſo we may ſerue him with the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12256:26"/>beſt member we haue. As <hi>Ioſeph</hi> charged the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarches, not to ſee his face, vnleſſe their brother <hi>Beniamin</hi> came with them: ſo ſtandeth the Lord affected to the heart: if thou wilt goe to the Lord goe with thy heart.<note place="margin">Ier. 29.13.</note> 
               <hi>Yee ſhall ſeeke and find me,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>becauſe yee ſhall ſeeke me with all your hearts.</hi> Thus did the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſecke the Lord, as he teſtifieth in his owne words,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.10.</note> 
               <hi>with my whole heart doe I ſeeke thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This condemnes hypocriticall ſeeking, which is deceitfull; It ſhall neuer finde acceptance with God, nor ſee his louely countenance. It drawes neare to God with the lips, and toucheth the creft of heauen (as it were) with the mouth, but the heart is far from God. If thy heart be not ſingle, then <hi>Peter</hi> in the perſon of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> hath read thy doome.<note place="margin">Act. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt no part in true Repentance, becauſe thy heart is not right in the ſight of God.</hi> If the old Pagan ſoothſayers at any time miſſed the heart in the entrailes of the Sacrifice, or if they found it without panting and moouing, they were wonderfully appauled, and ſtrongly feared that ſome danger would enſue. For they obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that in the ſacrifice of <hi>Iulius,</hi> the heart was wanting: and immediately after, his moſt famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar friends conſpired againſt him, and ſtabbed him in the Capitoll. They likewiſe obſerued in the ſacrifice of <hi>Pertinax,</hi> how the heart lay ſtill with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out motion, whoſe death preſently following, the people lamented with this wailing acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, While <hi>Pertinax</hi> raigned we liued ſecurely, and feared none. In our Chriſtian ſacrifice of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12256:26"/>prayers and repentance, alas, the heart is wanting, or at leaſt not ſtirring, there is ſo little faith, feare, obedience, zeale, ſinceritie among vs. What this heartleſſe ſeruing, ſeeking of God meaneth, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in particular diuine. I am no Prophet, nor the ſonne of a Prophet; yet ſure I am, it portends no good. For preuention therefore of imminent Iudgements, let vs ſeeke the Lord heartily,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.22.</note> giuing him the whole and entire poſſeſſion thereof, as himſelfe iuſtly cals for it ſaying,<note place="margin">Deut. 16.16.</note> 
               <hi>Turne yee vnto me with all your heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fourthly, in his Sonne Chriſt.</note>Fourthly, ſeeke God in his ſonne Chriſt, He is the onely Mediator that paſſeth betwixt God and vs, without whom none can come vnto, and find his Father. He is our <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder, whoſe huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie toucheth the earth, and his diuinitie reached to heauen. <hi>He is that new and liuing way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.20.</note> 
               <hi>through whom we haue acceſſe to the Father. He is the way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh 14.6.</note> 
               <hi>the truth, and the life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh:</hi> The way to him is faith; for,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>We walke by faith, not by ſight.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> He that ſeekes God to finde him muſt beleeue in him. We are a generation of ſeekers,<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.</note> of them that ſeeke the <hi>face of the God of Iacob.</hi> If we follow faith as our guide we ſhall neuer erre: yet miſtake me not, I meane not a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſolitary, imaginary fancie of faith; this is preſumption, not perſwaſion, but a ſauing, a ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying, a iuſtifying faith: a faith working by loue. This way to Chriſt hath the approbation of the Spirit, rounding the faithfull in the eare,<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.21.</note> 
               <hi>This is the way, walke in it,</hi> and long agoe prophecying
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12256:27"/>of it:<note place="margin">Iſa. 35.8.</note> 
               <hi>there ſhall be a way, and the way ſhall be called holy, the polluted ſhall not paſſe by it;</hi> Neither Lyon, nor Beare, nor any hurtfull creature ſhall walke in it. Therefore whoſoeuer <hi>walke according to this rule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>peace be vpon them, and mercie, and vpon the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This condemnes the Papiſts that ſeeke Gods fauour by other wayes then the true ſtatue Chriſt, the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and a number of their owne Canonized Saints make a way for them, thus ſay they; but Gods precious Oracle finds no tongue ſpeaking to this purpoſe: It onely ſheweth vs gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance to God, in, and through Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This alſo condemnes the Solifidians (yea Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifidians) that runne well but quite beſide the marke.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.23.</note> 
               <hi>Ahimaas</hi> by running the neareſt way out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtripped the Egyptian; and many make a ſhort but the way to him (leading through the intricate Mazes of this our Pilgrimage) is a ſound guiding faith: Make this thy rode, and then (though not ſo ſoone as thou wouldeſt) thou ſhalt ſee God in his brightneſſe of loue and mercie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fiftly, Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely.</note>Fiftly, Reſolutely; Reſolution is neceſſary to this point. The Souldiers reſolution is the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell: the Sowers reſolution is his plowing, and ſowing: the Schollers reſolution is his ſtudies: And all our reſolution ought to be this godly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to ſeeke the Lord. <hi>Let the dead bury the dead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil 3.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>I will follow hard towards the marke of the high calling. I will ſeeke God. Agrippa</hi> almoſt perſwaded to be a Chriſtian, was altogether no Chriſtian:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12256:27"/>vnſetledneſſe is the breake-necke of many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian courſes, when there is a purpoſe, and then no purpoſe, a will and no will to ſeeke God. It is not leaden heeles, but faint and dead hearts that makes vs ſtagger, and vntill the fire of determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, together with the hot coales of ſtedfaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution enflame vs onwards in our Inquiſition, we ſhall not enioy the promiſed <hi>Canaan,</hi> that land of fruitfulnes, where God is perpetually reſident. Therefore as <hi>Dauid ſwore and ſtedfaſtly purpoſed to keepe Gods righteous iudgements;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> ſo let his caſe be ours, that we may with full purpoſe bend our ſelues in Repentance to ſeeke the Lord, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer other occaſions and matters may caſually fall in our way.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, Directly; Beware of blind lanes,<note place="margin">Sixtly, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly.</note> and circuiting perambulations: crooked wayes and crooked feete will caſt backward.<note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> was ſhent for walking with a wry foote to the Goſpell. Therefore take heed to thy feet,<note place="margin">Eccl. 5.1. Heb. 12.13.</note> and <hi>make ſtraight pathes vnto them.</hi> The way to heauen is both ſtraite and ſtraight, like the <hi>ſtreete in Damaſcus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 9.11.</note> which was called the <hi>ſtraight ſtreete.</hi> He that goes about to ſeeke God, muſt goe as <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Coos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 21.1.</note> with a ſtraight courſe, therefore as thou art carefull to ſet on, ſo be as diligent to ſet out in the right and direct paſſages; leaue by-wayes and wrie-wayes to nocturnall walkers, perambulations and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuitions to Sathan, that infernall Peripatetike. Such as will obtaine Gods mercie, and finde his tokens of grace, muſt neither turne to the right hand of ſelfe-pleaſing ſingularitie,<note place="margin">Deut. 5.32.33.</note> nor to the left
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12256:28"/>hand of vulgar impietie: but walke in the true profeſſion of the Catholique faith, and in an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt vocation, warranted by Gods word.</p>
            <p>Seuenthly,<note place="margin">Seuenthly, Conſtantly. Math. 24 13.</note> Conſtantly; Continue ſeeking. <hi>He that continues to the end ſhall be ſaued.</hi> Gods grace is worth all our ſeeking, though we ſhould ſeeke it a thouſand yeare, giue not ouer till it be found. <hi>Be watchfull to the end and thou ſhalt haue the crowne of life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 2.10. And 2.26.</note> and he that <hi>keepeth my workes to the end, to him will I giue power ouer nations.</hi> What a ſhame is it then to recoile and fall off from ſeeking, bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backe <hi>like a broken Bow;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.57.</note> to begin in the ſpirit and end in the fleſh? What a ſhame is it after thou haſt fed on Angels food, to luſt after the Onions and Garlicke of Egypt? After thou haſt eſcaped the filthineſſe of the world, taſted of the good Word of God,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.5. 2 Pet. 2.21.22.</note> and of the ioyes to come, to <hi>turne from the holy Commandement, and with the dogge to returne to his vomit?</hi> What did it profit <hi>Demas</hi> to forſake the Goſpell, which once he profeſſed, and to turne worldling, which dearely he loued? Or the yong man to haue beene trayned vp in the keeping of the law,<note place="margin">Mar. 10.21.</note> and afterward to depart from Chriſt for the loue he had to his poſſeſſions? and what good ſhall we reape in ſeeking,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.9.</note> repenting, praying, humbling, hearing, &amp;c. if we faint and giue out before we obtaine the thing ſought? Like as he that runneth in a race,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.</note> vnleſſe he hold out to the goale, obtaineth not the price, and therefore ſayth <hi>Paul, I haue finiſhed my courſe,</hi> as it auailed not <hi>Lots</hi> wife to haue gone out of <hi>Sodome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.7.</note> and after to looke backe: So they ſhall neuer
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12256:28"/>come to the Lord, that lagger by the way, that are wearie of the dutie vndertaken, and runne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues out of breath, before they come to the end of their race. And if ſuch as ſeeke, but before the end giue out, ſhall not finde, what then ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of our wicked prophane wretches that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeeke at all? What ſhall become of them that ſeeke onely vanities? Which flie not, but ſeeke the corruption which is in the world, that care for nothing but backe and belly? If God reiect the righteouſnes and will of the Iewes, what hope canſt thou haue which neuer thinkeſt of God, but to blaſpheme him? Which delighteſt onely to wallow in abhominable ſinnes? I muſt tell thee that ten thouſand times thy betters are in hell, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſuch which haue rapt hard at heauen gates, which haue beſtowed many houres in prayers, much money on the poore, &amp;c. If ſuch as ſeeke, miſſe, for ſeeking amiſſe, much more thoſe that ſeeke not at all, or the contrary.</p>
            <p>This may aduiſe vs to <hi>renue our ſtrength as the Eagle, to waite on the Lord, to runne and not be weary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 112.6.</note> 
               <hi>to walke and not faint.</hi> Trees of the Lords planting continue their fruits indeficiently, neither doe their leaues drop off. Let vs be prouoked to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie in ſearching the Lord, and hereunto let vs conſider motiues, and meanes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Motiues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The end of Redemption is to follow the Lord,<note place="margin">Luk. 1.75.</note> to ſerue him in righteouſneſſe and holines all our dayes.<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.24.</note> 2. Righteouſneſſe departed from is vaine and forgotten. All labour, prayers, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12256:29"/>obedience, yea, all ſufferings are loſt, as the <hi>Galathians</hi> ſuffered many things in vaine.<note place="margin">Gal. 3.4.</note> 3. Thou ſhalt be iudged as thou art found when the Lord comes. The queſtion ſhall not be, what thou waſt once, but what thou art, not how thou began to ſeeke, but how thou continuedſt in Seeking. 4. Perſeuerance at length brings home the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, it knits vs indiſſolublie to the Lord, and puts vpon our heads the <hi>Crowne of glorie.</hi> Glory and immortalitie is the part onely of ſuch <hi>as by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in well doing ſeeke God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.7.</note> And our Sauiour is expreſſe,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.28.</note> 
               <hi>to you which haue continued with me haue I appointed a kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Meanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Get an infallible teſtimony of Gods fauour, ariſing from the wiſe application of Gods promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.40.</note> and the ſure witneſſe of his Spirit. 2. That thy ſelfe purified, make conſcience to repent of ſinne, and reſpect all Gods Commandements. 3. Continue the vſe of the meanes of preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as hearing, reading, praying, receiuing of the Sacraments, &amp;c. 4. Ioyne thy ſelfe with ſuch as daily ſeeke the Lord. 5. Labour to know the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary vſe and worth of the Lords preſence, that ſo thou maiſt confeſſe and profeſſe his goodneſſe amid humorous opinions and ſtrange oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. 6. Be not too hote and ouer-haſtie at firſt,<note place="margin">Nullum violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum perpetuum.</note> but meeke, tractable, ſociable, for boyſterous, and hot-ſpurred natures will not hold long. 7. Be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer warie, and circumſpect to walke on by feare, alwayes doubting thine owne weakneſſe, and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting thy ſtrength.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.12.</note> 
               <hi>Let him that ſtandeth take
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12256:29"/>heede leaſt he fall.</hi> Thus of our direction in ſeeking the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>While he may be found</hi>] There is a time (it ſeemes) when God will be found of his ſeruants that ſeeke him: It is his owne promiſe, and he will not gain-ſay it. <hi>The poore ſhall not alway be forgotten,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 9.18.</note> 
               <hi>the hope of the afflicted ſhall not periſh for euer.</hi> It makes God yearne within himſelfe to ſee the godly ſeek him in diſtreſſe,<note place="margin">Times to find God.</note> and himſelfe to with-hold his preſence from them. Therefore the firſt time wherein God will be found, is the godly mans exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and extremitie:<note place="margin">Deut. 4.29.30</note> 
               <hi>When thou art in tribulation</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes, and all theſe things are come vpon thee, at the length, if thou ſeeke the Lord, he will not forſake thee. Dauid</hi> called out of the deepe, and God heard him. <hi>Moſes</hi> cryed at the red Sea, and then God was found. <hi>Abraham</hi> three dayes after the Commandement, found God on the Mount. And after three dayes when the caſe was hopeleſſe, and the Diſciples faith a little preiudiced, Chriſt roſe againe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, another time of finding God, is the time of preaching Gods pure word, by it God knockes at the doore of our hearts,<note place="margin">Reu. 3.20.</note> and deſires entrance; By it he ſo reueales himſelfe to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, that they may ſpiritually by the illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated eye of the minde, behold him preſent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an admirable ſort among them. The time of preaching the Goſpell in Scripture is called the <hi>Day of viſitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, another time of finding, is when we haue vſed all godly exerciſes, &amp; heauenly meanes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12256:30"/>in ſeeking: for to ſit ſtill and doe nothing is to want the price. The Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi> wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her beloued, when ſhee would not ſollow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, but lay ſlugging on her bed. And when we are like ſtanding Ponds, couered with greene and filthie ſtuffe of idleneſſe, we are aliens from God. But when we fall to enquiring after him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the watchmen in the darke of the night, through dangerous ſtreets, with a good heart, eagarly, directly, reſolutely, continually, then he comes to vs, thruſts in his hand by the hole of the doore, calls vpon vs, and brings with him ſuch gracious gifts, as are worthie our paines and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> This may teach vs to cenſure charitably of the afflicted, and diſtreſſed in Conſcience: their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes may ſeeme ſo much to haue ſouced them, and they are ſo ſauced with the bitterneſſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward terrours, that to thy thinking God hath vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forſaken them. But I ſay learne to be wiſe, and deceiue not thy ſelfe. 1. There is a time wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God will be fauourable vnto them, wipe away their teares, and end their ſorrowes, which is beſt knowne to the Lord, perhaps it ſhall not be theſe many yeares,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.17.</note> or moneths: but ſure it ſhall come, and God will be preſent. 2. God loues an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſpirit,<note place="margin">Eſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 65.</note> yea, it is ſuch a thing that like an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damant it drawes him thither where it is. 3. God is the God of the afflicted, to giue them eaſe in his good time, he hath made his promiſe to them to be <hi>their couer from the raine, and a wall of defence from the ſtorme and tempeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:12256:30"/>
Beſides, conſider what may befall thy ſelfe, their caſe may be thine, God is able to burthen thee with the like griefes, and agonies, and therefore deale louingly, wiſely, and charitablie with them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, Is there a time when God will be found; then let no good and honeſt heart be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maied, though God be not preſent when it vſeth meanes: let it not obiect againſt God and ſay, <hi>Why hideſt thou thy ſelfe, O Lord?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 10.1.</note> For he is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes there at firſt call, neither will he grant (of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes) the requeſts of his people vpon two or three petitions, or many prayers, and it may be for their further good and profit.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. The Lord hereby will try their faith, and patience: <hi>Iob</hi> was tryed to the vttermoſt, before he found God taking his part, and ſo became an example of patience.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. They may hereby ſee the weightie Talent of their ſinnes, that hath preſſed them downe ſo farre from Gods face. If the Lord ſhould but lightly touch vs, we ſhould but ſleight our ſins.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Their deſire muſt be the more earneſt as his abſence is the more painfull; when the Spouſe had ſought Chriſt here and there, and could no where finde him, at length finding him ſhee tooke faſt hold on him, and would not let him goe.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Their prayer and paines is not worth the thing they ſeeke for, God will keepe it away for a time from them, that they may value it according to a faithfull eſteeme: and be more earneſt, and often in praying, and labour.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:12256:31"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. Or it may be, all this while God is abſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue not ſought him according to his will, or his Word, as <hi>Zebedees</hi> ſonnes, they asked they knew not what: or after ſuch a ſort, or in ſuch a thing as he will not be found in, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſought God to remoue away the pricke of the fleſh, yet God would not be found in that; but in the ſupply of ſufficient grace was he found.</p>
            <p>But for all this that I haue ſaid, God will be found of ſuch as ſeeke him in feare and awe, and after a good and godly manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi> But I am vnworthie to finde God,<note place="margin">Ob:</note> who haue prouoked his wrath like an vnkind wretch, and that euery day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ:</hi> Eſteeme not leſſe of thy ſelfe then God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemeth of thee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Act. 10.</note> in <hi>euery nation he that feareth him is found of him.</hi> He keepeth open houſe: his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Palace hath three gates in the Eaſt,<note place="margin">Reu. 21.</note> three in the Weſt, three in the North, three in the South, that the glory of Iewes &amp; Gentiles may come in: He thinketh not his owne preſence too good for vs:<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.26.</note> but <hi>where he is there ſhall his ſeruants be.</hi> This was his promiſe, becauſe it was his pleaſure. Therefore Chriſt ſaith to his Father.<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.24.</note> 
               <hi>Father I will that thoſe whom thou haſt giuen me be with me, that they may ſee that glory which thou haſt giuen me.</hi> With this hope he comforted his Diſciples; <hi>In my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe are many manſions, I goe to prepare a place for you;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>and if I goe to prepare a place for you, I will come againe and receiue you vnto me, that where I am there may yee alſo be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seeke God while he may be found</hi>] Another thing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12256:31"/>worthie obſeruation, is the opportunitie of ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo as God may be found, and that is the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time; Hence learne againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct:</hi> The preſent time is Gods time. Eccleſ. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that <hi>the moſt ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſeaſon to ſeeke God is the preſent ſeaſon.</hi> There <hi>is a time for each thing vnder the Sunne,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> but for this dutie, no time ſo conuenient as the very inſtant. In worldly buſineſſe delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is very neceſſary, &amp; it is held a great point of policie to deliberate long before a man deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine any thing: but in this caſe it is dangerous to ſtand to deliberate.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> 1. Becauſe to deferre is vaine and fond pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. I neede not yet ſeeke God ſayth the yongſter, nor repent, nor pray, nor doe well,<note place="margin">Delay is vaine and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous.</note> &amp;c. It is not good to be religious too ſoone, for feare yong Saints proue old Deuils: when I am growne old then I will bethinke my ſelfe of this matter. Vpon this in-bred preſumption he is all for to morrow, crying out with <hi>Domitians</hi> Crow, <hi>Cras, cras,</hi> to morrow, to morrow, when as <hi>he knoweth not what the morrow may bring forth,</hi> Conuerſion, or Confuſion.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou. 27.1.</hi> Quamdiu cras, cras, quare non modo, quare non hac hora finis turpitudinis meae.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in that excellent Booke of his Confeſſions, ſpeaketh to all yong men in his owne perſon, perſwading them not to deferre this good worke. How long, ſaith he, ſhall I ſay to morrow to morrow? Why doe I not now? Why do I not now make an end of this filthines? Yea,<note place="margin">Qui non eſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, cras minus aptus erit. Sera nimis vita eſt craſtina, viue hodie, &amp;c.</note> the very Heathen Poets haue condemned this procraſtination, and would haue men to lay hold on the preſent time. It was good counſell which good <hi>Eleazar</hi> gaue his Diſciples;<note place="margin">Ouid. Marr. Perſ.</note> 
               <hi>Be ſure yee repent one day before death.</hi> When replie was
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12256:32"/>made, the day of death is vncertaine, therefore he ſaid repent this day leaſt to morrow yee die. Thus ſtands our caſe.<note place="margin">D: Hulls Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at the Croſſe. Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tob. 18. 1612.</note> A poore traueller by chance ſlips <q>into a pit, and in his fall catches hold of one twigge. The pit is deepe, and in the bottome full of cruell Serpents. While there he hangeth by that poore twig, anon comes an hunger-bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten beaſt, which byting, and browzing on other boughes, is each moment ready to crop off that twig: Now in what a wofull plight is this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed creature. This traueller is man, the ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der twig is fraile life, this pit is hell, thoſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, fiends, and wormes of Conſcience, the hunger-bitten beaſt is death:</q> Say now were it not fooliſh preſumption to deferre Repentance vpon hope of long life, depending on ſo doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full condition? Many yong men are taken away on the ſudden, before euer they looke, or prepare for death.<note place="margin">Iob. 21.13. And 24.24.</note> 
               <hi>They ſpend their daies in wealth and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly they goe downe to the graue, and are cropt off as an eare of Corne.</hi> Haue we not examples euery day almoſt of ſome that goe well to bed at night, and are found dead in the morning? And of others that drop downe by the high way ſide, and die in the field? We may not take vpon vs to determine peremptorily of ſuch,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.33.</note> becauſe <hi>the iudgements of God are vnſearchable, and his wayes paſt finding out.</hi> Therefore adde not one euill day vnto another. <hi>Sufficient for the day is the euill thereof:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> yeſterday, to day, to morrow, time paſt, preſent, and to come, that is, all the dayes of our life are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> dayes of ſorrow.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:12256:32"/>
2. Delay is danderous: breeds ſecond nature,<note place="margin">2. Delay is dangerous.</note> and cuſtome of euill, whereon God vſually layeth a fearefull commination;<note place="margin">Reu. 22.11.</note> 
               <hi>Let him that is filthie be filthie ſtill.</hi> And when the ſoule is invred to an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill habit, it is hardly capable of better impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and vertuous diſpoſitions.<note place="margin">Ier. 13.23.</note> 
               <hi>Can the Black-moore change his skin, or the Leopard his ſpots? So hard it is for them to doe well who haue learned to doe euill.</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> long acquainted with <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage, were loath to leaue it; but the hurt was their owne, &amp; their loſſe had beene greater if the Lord had not redeemed them with a ſtrong arme. When ſinne pleads preſcription, and Sathan poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, the Soule of the Combatant ſhall finde enough to doe to be rid of it; for, his <hi>bones were filled with the ſinnes of his youth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 20.11.</note> 
               <hi>and now they will ſleepe with him in the duſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reaſon</hi> 3. It is diſaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</note>3. Deferred ſeeking is diſmall and diſaſterous. He that neglects to day ſhall haue no time to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,<note place="margin">Ren. 10.6.</note> but ſhall for his negligence purchaſe an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of diſpleaſure. The rich man, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed himſelfe many dayes of pleaſure;<note place="margin">Luk. 12.19.</note> 
               <hi>But thou foole</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>this night ſhall they fetch away thy ſoule.</hi> And many a man feeds his conceit with an Euening Conuerſion, and with the Backe, to ſpread his wings of Repentance in the twi-light; but that is not Gods houre, and therefore his head and heart may ake with crying, but ſhall not be the better, for he ſhall end his dayes in woe: this is an approued truth,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.17.</note> 
               <hi>Eſan</hi> ſought the bleſſing in vaine, <hi>though he ſought it with teares, when there was no place for Repentance.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> The fiue fooliſh Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12256:33"/>comming too late, when the Bridegroome was entred, and the doore ſhut, had a fearefull and finall repulſe, <hi>I know yee not;</hi> When I called, yee anſwered not;<note place="margin">Prou. 1.28.</note> when I ſaid, <hi>Returne to me yee ſonnes of Adam, yee would not returne:</hi> therefore <hi>when you ſhall call vpon me I will not anſwere; when you ſeeke me early I will not be found, &amp;c.</hi> Oh, therefore let vs not waſt away that little light of time left vs, in gaming, ryoting, reuelling, drinking, dauncing, dallying, ſwaggering, ſwearing, &amp;c. but take pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent hold on it ſo friendly ſmyling; for, as Chriſt ſayd of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt, This is Eliah, if yee will receiue him;</hi> So, I ſay, This is the time of our repentance, euen this houre, this minute, this moment.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> For the performance of this ſpeed requiring dutie,<note place="margin">The precepts and examples of others may moue to this dutie.</note> we neither want ſufficient Precepts, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of others. Firſt, we haue many incite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and precepts. 1. Of Chriſt. <hi>Walke in the light while yee haue the light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 12.35. And 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>for the night commeth when no man can worke. Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, would to God that in this thy day, &amp;c.</hi> 2. Of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who all are ſo nearely conioyned in vrging the preſent opportunitie, that they need not be rehearſed,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.16. Prou. 23.23. 1 Pet. 5.</note> counſelling vs in generall to <hi>buy the truth, but not to ſell it, to redeeme the time, to gird vp our loines, &amp;c.</hi> Secondly, we haue ſtore of exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples vnto this dutie, as 1. of Chriſt, who like a Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antran his race, and as the Sunne in the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he <hi>went about preaching the word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 4.23.</note> 
               <hi>doing good, and healing all diſeaſes among the people.</hi> He gaue his eyes no ſleepe, his eye-lids no ſlumber, nor the temples of his head any reſt, vntill his Father
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12256:33"/>gaue him his <hi>Quietus eſt: Sit thou on my right hand.</hi> 2. Of the Angels, who attend the Lord, and doe his heaſts and his will at the firſt command with ſpeed, they make no delayes, but when the Lords pleaſure is to doe his meſſage they runne. 3. Of holy and godly men, to whom as ſoone as the Lord ſayth, <hi>Seeke my face,</hi> they forthwith addreſſe themſelues to it, and ſhape this anſwere,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.6.</note> 
               <hi>Thy face Lord will we ſeeke. Zacheus</hi> being bidden to <hi>come downe from the tree, came downe haſtily, and receiued Chriſt ioyfully.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 31.</note> When God charged <hi>Iacob</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into the land of his Fathers, and to his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, he protracted no time, but informing <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hell</hi> and <hi>Lea</hi> of the neceſſitie of his voyage, he ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly departed, without taking his leaue of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban;</hi> and the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth of himſelfe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.60.</note> I <hi>conſidered my wayes, and turned my feete vnto thy te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, I made haſte, and delayed not the time, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, we are taught from the vnreaſonable creatures, to obſerue our time,<note place="margin">Ier. 8.8.</note> 
               <hi>The Storke knoweth her appointed time, the ſwallow her ſeaſon.</hi> Why ſhould we that are endowed with reaſon neglect the gracious time, <hi>why ſtand we idle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 20.</note> 
               <hi>or ſit we gap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one on another?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 42.1.</note> Let vs put on <hi>the ſhooes of the preparation of the Goſpell on our feete,</hi> and let vs take the ſtaues of trauellers in our hands, that ſo we may make haſt to him, who will crowne our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe imputed by Chriſt, with glory and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> This Doctrine makes againſt all ſuch as haue a iuſt opportunitie of Repentance, and yet driue it off. Some are viſited with the weightie hand of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12256:34"/>God, through ſickneſſe, infirmities, loſſes, &amp;c. One would thinke this time would wholly preſſe their Conſciences with this ſo good a dutie, and vrge a perſeuerance of humiliation, but yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, no ſooner is Gods hand remoued from them, but like Horſes well fatted, and pampered, they kicke againſt their maiſter, and fall to tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in their out-caſted dung. Others vnder the painefull Miniſtery, and while the zeale thereof ſeemes to touch them, are all on the ſpurre, they will cry, and take on as if they were vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, they will ſeeme to reforme all whatſoeuer hath beene done amiſſe; but like ſtubborne and deceitfull ſeruants, (that ſtand ſilent and mute be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their maſters) they will laugh, and ſpend time idlie, and laſciuiouſly, when they are departed from it: they forget the word, yea, themſelues, and ſo with the dogge <hi>they returne to their wonted vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.22.</note> Others are in ſtrength of bodie and ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the members, and they need not returne to God till they waxe wan, and weake, and feeble: and then (they ſay) is their time. But let me frame ſuch an opponent and times-enemie this anſwere; if thou doeſt not forſake thy ſinnes, and turne to God till thou be weake and feeble, then thy ſinnes will forſake thee, and not thou them: What thankes is it for a drunkard to giue ouer his drunkenneſſe, when he is not able any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to goe to the Alehouſe? Or for the Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter to leaue his whoredome, when he hath no ſtrength for the performance, and execution of his filthie deſire? A man ſhould willingly part
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12256:34"/>with his ſinnes euen while he is able to commit them, and not by conſtraint when there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie. Secondly, the time of weakneſſe, dotage, &amp;c. is not Gods appointed opportunitie: If a man would then he cannot ſoundly turne to God, for all the parts of bodie, and powers of ſoule will looſe their vertue, and neither part nor power can performe their office.<note place="margin">Eceleſ. 12.</note> The brawne of the armes they fall away; the keepers of the houſe,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that is, the hands which defend the bodie trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; the ſtrong men, that is, the legges that ſhould carry the bodie, doe bow themſelues, and waxe faint, the eyes that looke out at the windowes are darke, and obſcure, the Grinders, that is, the teeth,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> fall out of the head: the doores of the lips are ſhut, the iawes fallen, and the daughters of ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that is, the eares are abaſed, being vnable any longer to heare the ſound of Muſicke: the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie is dulled, the vnderſtanding darkned, &amp;c. And further leaſt a man ſhould thinke the time of dotage, and of weakneſſe the moſt conuenient time to ſeeke the Lord, <hi>Salomon</hi> brings in that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepit age, deafe, blind, lame, halt, ſhort winded, full of aches in his bones, cramps in his ioynts, and ſundry diſeaſes in his bodie, trembling on a ſtaffe, with ſhaking lips, and almoſt robbed of all ſenſes; as if he might ſay, Now looke, and tell me whether this weake time, this feeble age, be the acceptable time and day of conuerſion? When this age oppreſſed <hi>Barzillai,</hi> then could he ſay, <hi>Can I diſcerne betweene good and euill?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam 19.35.</note> 
               <hi>Haue I any taſte in that I eate or drinke, &amp;c.</hi> He confeſſed that
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12256:35"/>his weakneſſe was ſo great, that both bodie and mind were diſabled from attending on the King, much more from attending this worke of grace. Others alſo are readie to plead the mercifulneſſe of God, to giue toleration to preſumptuous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſtination: Oh, God is mercifull, hereupon the yong man is looſe, the drunkard ryotous, the rich man cruell, the ſwearer blaſphemous, the adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer vicious, and each man adulterate and beaſtiall in his kinde; But let ſuch bold flinder-mice know withall, that God is as ſpeedie in iuſtice to puniſh the euill and vngodly men, as he is full of mercie for the vſe and reward of his owne dearelings. The hope of the wicked is hopeleſſe, the Lord hath ſaid it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 18.26. Prou. 1.28 34.</note> he will viſit <hi>their iniquities, and laugh at their deſtruction;</hi> and they ſhall finde that true (for all their preſumptions) which the Apoſtle relateth,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.32. And 12.29. Rom. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>it is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of God, who is a conſuming fire. The mercie of God ſhould lead men to repentance, and make prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the day of grace.</hi> Others are forward to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe their delay. I pray you, did not the theefe on the Croſſe ſeeke the Lord by Repentance at the laſt houre of his life, and found him to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort? I grant its true, but it followes not thereon that euery one ſo ſeeking ſhall partake of GODS fauour. This example was extraordinary, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of God, that ſinners ſhould not preſume, and that true paenitentiaries ſhould not deſpaire. It is folly and great madneſſe to deferre vntill the laſt, in regard of this one patterne and example, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing left without precept. Fie on this ſlaggering
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12256:35"/>and ſtaggering of Chriſtians, who gape after Meteors in the aire, caſt beyond the Moone, and are doubtfull, when they hazard nothing but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, which would hazard their ſoules. They murmure at preſent conuerſion, and ſay with the Diſciples, <hi>This is an hard ſaying, who can beare it?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.</note> Or elſe they ſeeke to ſhift it off as they did, who were called on to re-edifie the Temple, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>It is not yet time to build,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hag. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, this Doctrine may likewiſe ſerue for Inſtruction;<note place="margin">For inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> God biddeth, and it is our dutie to hold opportunitie by the fore-locke, by a little ſtaying behind, it will ſlip away, and we ſhall not be able to catch hold of it. Now the Lord will be found, but anon he is gone, and will abſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as the Prophet tells vs,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 5.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>They ſhall goe with their ſheepe and their Bullockes to ſeeke the Lord, but they ſhall not find him, for he hath with-drawne himſelfe from them.</hi> Oh, therefore when God putteth any good motion into our hearts of ſeeking, let vs forthwith addreſſe our ſelues vnto it, as <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeruant that was ſent to prouide a wife for his ſon <hi>Iſaac,</hi> when he had had good ſucceſſe, and well effected the buſineſſe which he came for, haſted home to his Maſter: And when <hi>Rebeccaes</hi> friends requeſted him to ſtay ten dayes, becauſe they were loath to part with her on the ſodaine, he would not yeeld at any hand: <hi>No, hinder me not,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">Gen. 34.54.55.56.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeing the Lord hath proſpered my iourney, but ſend me away that I may goe to my Maſter:</hi> So ſhould we ſuffer nothing at all to hinder vs, but euen make haſt to turne to the Lord vpon the firſt motion.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12256:36"/>There is a good ſaying to this purpoſe in the booke of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>Make no tarrying to ſeeke the Lord, and put not off from day to day, for ſodainly ſhall the wrath of the Lord breake forth, and in thy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie thou ſhalt be deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi> But it will be ſaid,<note place="margin">Ob:</note> 
               <hi>Haſt makes waſt, faire and ſoftly goe farre, ſoft fire makes ſweet Malt, the haſtie man neuer wanted woe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ:</hi> All theſe be true,<note place="margin">Anſ.</note> and good often in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall affaires, yea, and ſometimes alſo in buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes touching the ſoule;<note place="margin">Eſay. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Let not him that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth make haſte;</hi> be not too credulous of euery thing without triall. But in this caſe of ſeeking the Lord, theſe Prouerbes hold not true, we haue no larger bounds then the preſent, the inſtant, the moment. If we ſlacke our zeale neuer ſo little, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery baite of drunkenneſſe, obiect of couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, preſented glance of wantonneſſe, will offer it ſelfe as a temptation, to alter, or at leaſt, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our intended Conuerſion. And albeit, they ſay as the Deuils ſaid to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Why tormenteſt thou vs before the time?</hi> Yet brethren, the time is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die come, and now is, wherein God conuerſeth with vs moſt graciouſly by his Spirit, and moſt familiarly by his word, let vs therefore gather <hi>Manna</hi> early in the morning before the Sunne melt it away, and let vs walke in the light while we haue it, then ſhall our darkeneſſe be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to light, our ſorrow into ioy, our baldneſſe into beautie, and for ſack-cloath we ſhall be decked with garments of gladneſſe; then ſhall heauen
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12256:36"/>and earth, Angels and men, and all creatures elſe clap their hands for ioy of our Conuerſion, all meeting in this cloze. Prayſed be the Lord, (who hath ſuch pleaſure in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants) that he will be found of them to their Saluation.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12256:37"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12256:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
